<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Solomon's Proverbs English and Latin, alphabetically collected for help of memory. / In English by H.D. ; and since made Latin by S. Perkins ... ; Fitted for the use of schools.</title>
            <author>Danvers, Henry, d. 1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2633E</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175390</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097565</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097565</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171177)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2564:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Solomon's Proverbs English and Latin, alphabetically collected for help of memory. / In English by H.D. ; and since made Latin by S. Perkins ... ; Fitted for the use of schools.</title>
                  <author>Danvers, Henry, d. 1687.</author>
                  <author>Perkins, Samuel, fl. 1625-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The fifth edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[169] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Redmayne, and are to be sold by Hen. Mortlock at the Phœnix in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>English and Latin on opposite pages.</note>
                  <note>H.D. is Henry Danvers. Cf. NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>"Collected out of the Proverbs and Ecclesiastes"--P. [8].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs. --  English. --  Selections. --  1684.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs. --  Latin. --  Selections. --  1684.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes. --  English. --  Selections. --  1684.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes. --  Latin. --  Selections. --  1684.</term>
               <term>Proverbs in the Bible.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171177:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SOLOMON'S</hi> PROVERBS <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> Alphabetically Collected for help of Memory.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>H. D.</hi> And ſince made <hi>Latin</hi> by <hi>S. Perkins,</hi> late School-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Chriſt-Church-Hoſpital.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fitted for the Uſe of Schools.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 12.9.</hi>
               </bibl> The Preacher was wiſe, he taught the People Knowledge; yea, he gave good heed, and ſought out, and ſet in order many Proverbs.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Kings 4.30, 31, 32.</hi>
               </bibl> And Solomon's Wiſdom excelled the wiſdom of all the Children of the Eaſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For he was wiſer than all the Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And he ſpake three thouſand Proverbs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 4.7.</hi>
               </bibl> Wiſdom is the Principal thing, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore get Wiſdom; and with all thy gettings, get Underſtanding.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fifth Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Redmayne,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Hen. Mortlock</hi> at the <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1681.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171177:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171177:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171177:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſaid of</hi> Solomon, <hi>ſo much commended for WISDOM, 1</hi> Kings <hi>4.29.</hi> &amp;c. That God gave him wiſdom and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exceeding much, and largeneſs of heart, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as the ſand that is on the Sea-Shore. And that his wiſdom excelled the wiſdom of the Children of the Eaſt-Country, and all the wiſdom of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And, that he was wiſer than all men <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And, that his fame was in all Nations round about: <hi>Which admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wiſdom of his ſeemed chiefly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in his Proverbs;</hi> Who ſpake, <hi>as Verſ. 32.</hi> three thouſand Proverbs; <hi>compared with</hi> Eccl. <hi>12.9.</hi> The Preacher was wiſe, he ſtill taught the people knowledge; yea, he gave good heed, and ſought out and ſet in order many Proverbs.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:171177:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> The nature of a Proverb.</head>
               <p>For the Nature of them in general. They are ſhort wiſe Sentences, containing much in a little. The <hi>Hebrew</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſimilitudo, parabola, proverbium ſententia: citè gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter que dicta &amp; paucis concinnata. <hi>Bux. Lex.</hi>
                  </note> ſignifies (as <hi>Buxt.</hi>) an excellent Speech, Sentence, Parable, or Similitude, acutely and weightily ſpoke and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized in few words. The <hi>Greek</hi> words,<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Proverbium, Adagium,</hi> Ep. 222. <hi>Parabola,</hi> Joh. 10.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. <hi>Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio alegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca &amp; aenigmatica,</hi> Mat. 13.13. 2. <hi>Obſcura ſententia,</hi> Mat. 15.15. 3. <hi>Exemplar ſeu Typus,</hi> Heb. 9.9. 4. <hi>Adagium.</hi> Luk. 4.23. 5. <hi>Similitudo.</hi> Heb. 11.11. <hi>Paſ. Lex.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>vel</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Paſor</hi> renders them, import much the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> ſhort Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, ſometimes comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered, called by <hi>Greek</hi> Writers, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Axioms,</hi> or worthy ſayings; and by the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins Adagia,</hi> Adagies, ſhort Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:4"/>In the Scripture ſometimes called, <hi>The ſayings of the Antients,</hi> 1 Sam. 24.13. becauſe delivered by the wiſe ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers or Elders, and therefore <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.6. called, <hi>The words of the wiſe;</hi> and ſometimes, <hi>The ſayings of old,</hi> 2 Sam. 20.18. Pſal. 78.2. becauſe the approbation and conſent of Ages went to make them the uſuage of a Nation, being brought by Cuſtom and Tradition to every mouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of a Proverb.</head>
               <p>Proverbs we find are variouſly laid down and uſed in Scripture, ſometimes by way of <hi>Compariſon</hi> or <hi>Similitude,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively.</hi>
                  </note> which doth greatly illuſtrate, as <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.9. <hi>As a Thorn goeth up into the haend of a Drunkard, ſo is a Parable in the mouth of Fools.</hi> And verſ. 11. <hi>As a Dog returneth to his vomit; ſo a Fool retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to his folly.</hi> Ver. 14. <hi>As a Door turneth upon his Hinges, ſo doth the ſlothful man up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Bed. Be wiſe as Serpents, and harmleſs as Doves,</hi> Mat. 10.16.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:5"/>
                  <note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a <hi>Proverb</hi> and a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi>
                  </note>And the only difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt this ſort of Proverbs and Parables is, That one is a large ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, the other a ſhort one. A Parable is a long Proverb, and a Proverb a ſhort Parable; being in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture therefore called both by one name, ſometimes the Parable called Proverb, and the Proverb called Parable, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.15.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour delighted ſo much in this kind of ſpeaking, that he is ſaid not to have ſpoke without them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.34.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely.</hi>
                  </note>Sometimes in an obſcure or aenigmatick way of ſpeaking, and therefore called, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.6. <hi>The words of the wiſe, and their dark ſayings.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.2. <hi>Dark ſayings of old;</hi> which our Saviour therefore uſually explained, as not being underſtood many times by his Auditors, as <hi>John</hi> 10.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.11,—15, 16, 17 <hi>ver. Mar.</hi> 13.11. And therefore it is ſaid to him upon his explanation, <hi>John</hi> 16.26. <hi>Now ſpeakeſt thou plainly, and ſpeakeſt no Proverb,</hi> oppoſing plain ſpeaking to proverbial or Paribolical.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:5"/>Sometimes again in a plain fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſtile,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Plainly.</hi>
                  </note> eaſie to be underſtood of all; containing ſhort, pithy, ſententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Doctrines, either for inſtruction, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, admonition or reproof: And of this kind are moſt of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s, and indeed moſt we meet with in the Scriptures: as ſuch as theſe: <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wiſdom. Above all gettings, get underſtanding. Fools make a mock of ſin. Man lives not by bread alone. Evil commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication corrupts good manners.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> The End of a Proverb.</head>
               <p>The end of a Proverb is for information of the mind, and reformation of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and beſt expreſt by <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf, in his own words, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.2, 3. <hi>To know Wiſdom and Inſtruction; to perceive the words of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding; to receive the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Wiſdom, Juſtice, Judgment and Equity.</hi> And this Univerſally to all ſorts, degrees, age and ſexes, young and old, poor and rich, learned and unlearned, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and wiſe; therefore verſ. 45. <hi>To give
<pb facs="tcp:171177:6"/>
ſubtility to the ſimple; to the young man, knowledg and diſcretion. To the wiſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, increaſe of learning, and the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to wiſe Counſels; to the underſtanding of a Proverb, or an eloquent Speech,</hi> (as the Margent) <hi>the words of the Wiſe, and their dark Sayings.</hi> It is ſaid, the wiſdom of the Ancient <hi>Grecians,</hi> that wiſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Nation, conſiſted much in their <hi>Proverbs;</hi> and to this day they are accounted the beſt evidence of the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of a Nation, whereof Collections are generally made, and Records uſually kept.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> The Order of <hi>Solomon's</hi> Proverbs.</head>
               <p>As for the Order of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s <hi>Proverbs,</hi> they are without any methodical contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or near dependance upon each other, which makes them the more abſtruſe, and difficult to the Reader; are therefore, for better help of Memory, brought into this method and order, being Alphabetically collected out of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> and <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes;</hi> and though deſigned only for private uſe, is here tendred to the publick, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
<pb facs="tcp:171177:6"/>
for all; but eſpecially recommended to the wiſe improvement of Judicious School-maſters, by whoſe ingenuity, theſe excellent Adagies, and worthy ſayings, ſo full of Wiſdom and knowledge, ſo expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leading to every duty, both to God, our ſelves and Neighbours, and of ſuch Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal concern, may by Gods bleſſing be improved in School-learning, to inſtil ſuch excellent Principles as may not only leave divine impreſſions upon the minds of their youth, but moſt admirably direct to every moral accompliſhment, containing not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the true wiſdom, (teaching the fear of the Lord) but all other neceſſary learning, as well <hi>Ethicks, viz.</hi> matters pertaining to moral vertues, as Prudence, Juſtice, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As <hi>Oeconomicks, viz.</hi> matters of Domeſtick or Family concerns, relating to the duties of husbands, wives, Parents, Children, Maſters and Servants. And <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks</hi> alſo, relating to Government, and matters of State: ſo that <hi>Plato, Ariſtotle, Cicero,</hi> &amp;c. and other Heatheniſh School-Authors, are not to be named with <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:7"/>
who ſo inſtructs to every good word and work; the <hi>Proverbs</hi> indeed being what is ſaid of the Scriptures, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore, as <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf adviſes, <hi>Train up a Child in the way he ſhould go, and when he is old he will not depart from it,</hi> Prov. 22.6.</p>
               <p>If any advantage be reaped hereby to to you or yours, let God have the Glory, and the unworthy Inſtrument the benefit of your Prayers, who is deſirous in every capacity faithfully to his utmoſt,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>To ſerve You and his Generation, whilſt, <hi>H. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:171177:7"/>
            <head>Of Wiſdom.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THE great Jehovah, who inhabits light,</l>
               <l>Appear'd to <hi>Solomon</hi> in a dream by night,</l>
               <l>And ſaid, Ask now what I ſhall give to thee?</l>
               <l>Suppoſe now (Mortals) this ſame queſtion be</l>
               <l>Propos'd to you, Let's hear, what would you ſay?</l>
               <l>And how would you diſpoſe your choice, I pray?</l>
               <l>Give me (ſaith one) in Riches to abound:</l>
               <l>Give me (ſaith t'other) Honour and Renown.</l>
               <l>But what ſaith <hi>Solomon?</hi> O Lord impart</l>
               <l>To me a wiſe and underſtanding heart.</l>
               <l>Wiſe was thy choice, wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> to which</l>
               <l>God therefore added to be Great and Rich.</l>
               <l>The wiſeſt Lord did know, that only he</l>
               <l>Could rightly uſe both Wealth and Dignity,</l>
               <l>Who ſteer'd his courſe by wiſdoms ſage advice;</l>
               <l>Here's the true Honour, here's the Pearl of price.</l>
               <l>For what's a Fool, that is with riches grac'd,</l>
               <l>A Swine, in whoſe fowl ſnowt a Gem is plac'd.</l>
               <l>Or what's a Fool, on whom honour doth wait?</l>
               <l>A long ear'd-Aſs ſitting in Chair of State.</l>
               <l>The Miſer is a fool, and ſo is he</l>
               <l>That ſpends his wealth in prodigality:</l>
               <l>Whom, if they went to Wiſdom, ſhe would ſhow</l>
               <l>A fair and middle path wherein to go.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:8"/>And art thou great? be not a fool, for thus</l>
               <l>Thou'lt make thy folly more conſpicuous.</l>
               <l>Acquaint they ſelf with Wiſdom, wait upon her,</l>
               <l>And ſhe will add true glory to thine honour.</l>
               <l>By her Kings reign, and Princes do decree</l>
               <l>By her advice, Juſtice and Equity.</l>
               <l>A fool that is in honour doth but ſhow</l>
               <l>Himſelf to be a fool in Folio.</l>
               <l>May n't <hi>Rehoboam</hi> juſtly ſtiled be,</l>
               <l>A famous fool, a fool in high degree?</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Iſraels</hi> ten Tribes forſook becauſe</l>
               <l>He wilfully forſook grave Wiſdoms Laws;</l>
               <l>While be th' advice of Seniors refus'd,</l>
               <l>And the raſh counſel of the Young Men us'd?</l>
               <l>Juſtly might Wiſdom then preferred be</l>
               <l>By <hi>Solomon,</hi> 'bove wealth and dignity:</l>
               <l>With him ſhe, above all, the Conqueſt won,</l>
               <l>Wiſdom was juſtified by her Son:</l>
               <l>Into whoſe breaſts ſhe did a flame inſpire,</l>
               <l>Which will laſt longer than the Veſtal fire;</l>
               <l>A ſacred flame it is, which ne're will die,</l>
               <l>But ev'n now burns for us to warm us by:</l>
               <l>A flame that gives not only heat but light,</l>
               <l>Not only warms the heart, but guides the ſight.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O Peerleſs Wiſdom!</hi> teach us how to prize thee,</l>
               <l>That wealth nor honour may not equallize thee;</l>
               <l>Without thee they are worſe than nothing; Thou</l>
               <l>Art without them both wealth and honour too.</l>
               <l>That we may know thy worth, let's ſearch and ſee,</l>
               <l>From whence thou doſt derive thy Pedegree.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:8"/>Though equal honour be not to thee given,</l>
               <l>Yet thou'rt the off-ſpring of the King of Heaven,</l>
               <l>Wiſdom doth ſhine in all his works, which he</l>
               <l>Grants man ſometimes through Wiſdoms glaſs to ſee.</l>
               <l>View now and read, Natures great Volumn, look</l>
               <l>Wiſdom's in every leaf of Natures Book.</l>
               <l>Behold how ſhe hath knit the whole Creation</l>
               <l>In a moſt glorious link to admiration.</l>
               <l>They're happy who with Contemplations eye</l>
               <l>The hidden ſecrets of her glory ſpie.</l>
               <l>O fooliſh man, that didſt not know her price,</l>
               <l>But didſt forſake her, and ſo Paradiſe:</l>
               <l>Whoſe mind the miſts of Ignorance now cloud,</l>
               <l>While ſhe in Heaven doth her glory ſhroud.</l>
               <l>Yet God (whom goodneſs doth delight) hath given</l>
               <l>A Palace to her here beneath the Heaven;</l>
               <l>That man (who did deſpiſe her glory) might</l>
               <l>In darkneſs ſee his folly by her light;</l>
               <l>A light, O bleſſed light, that ſhews the way,</l>
               <l>From which blind man hath ſo long gone aſtray,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But where doth Wiſdoms Palace ſtand, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>For this therefore, liſten a while (I pray)</l>
               <l>T' a Pilgrim, who hath wandered about,</l>
               <l>And ſought to find this famous Palace out.</l>
               <l>I went not far, when lo! I did eſpie,</l>
               <l>Far off, a Fabrick, beauteous to my eye,</l>
               <l>In a fair Proſpect: I approacht therefore,</l>
               <l>And ſaw men crown'd with Lawrel at the door;</l>
               <l>They call'd them Poets: who, when as they knew</l>
               <l>I ſought for Wiſdoms Palace, all the crew</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:9"/>Cry'd out, <hi>Pray enter, and it will appear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That Wiſdom (whom you ſeek for) dwelleth here.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I entred then, and ſaw at my ingreſs,</l>
               <l>Rooms garniſh'd to the life, I muſt confeſs;</l>
               <l>What Carvers art, or Painters skill could doe,</l>
               <l>Was repreſented there unto my view.</l>
               <l>But where's the Room where Wiſdom doth abide,</l>
               <l>Wherein ſhe doth her beams of glory hide?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>She's in that Room,</hi> (ſaid they) ſo in I came;</l>
               <l>Loe t'was a Strumpet there, <hi>Fancy</hi> by Name,</l>
               <l>Whoſe whole Attire was very gay and ſpruce,</l>
               <l>Yet very wanton, and her geſtures looſe;</l>
               <l>Yet theſe ſame fooliſh Poets fell before her,</l>
               <l>And, as a Goddeſs, did they all adore her.</l>
               <l>Farewel (ſaid I) for yet it don't appear,</l>
               <l>That Wiſdom (whom I ſeek for) dwelleth here.</l>
               <l>Soon I went my journey, till my haſt,</l>
               <l>Had brought me to a certain place at laſt,</l>
               <l>In which I ſaw men arguing together,</l>
               <l>Who aked me, What 'twas that brought me thither?</l>
               <l>To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for Wiſdom, I reply'd: but they</l>
               <l>(Men called them Philoſophers) did ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Enter this Palace, and it will appear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That Wiſdom (whom you ſeek for) dwelleth here.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I entered in, the Rooms did ſhine with Gold,</l>
               <l>And were all very glorious to behold:</l>
               <l>But yet although 'twas Gold unto my view,</l>
               <l>I fear the Gold was counterfeit, not true.</l>
               <l>And here and there were plac'd in divers ſtations,</l>
               <l>Both grave advices, and fine ſpeculations,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:9"/>I could not ſee diſtinctly; for my ſight</l>
               <l>Was only guided by the Candle light</l>
               <l>Of nature— But where's Wiſdom? <hi>O repair</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Replyed they) to that Chamber, for ſhe's there.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yea, this is ſhe, ſaid I; but coming nigh,</l>
               <l>I could no ſigns of life or motion ſpie;</l>
               <l>But ſaw ſhe was an Image made by Art,</l>
               <l>Aſſimilating Wiſdom in each part.</l>
               <l>O then, thought I, true Wiſdom life hath got,</l>
               <l>And is from God above, but this is not.</l>
               <l>Farewell (ſaid I) for yet it don't appear,</l>
               <l>That Wiſdom (whom I ſeek for) dwelleth here.</l>
               <l>So I departed thence with ſpeedy feet,</l>
               <l>Whenas I found that was not Wiſdoms Seat.</l>
               <l>And in my progreſs, I at laſt did ſee,</l>
               <l>Some perſons wearing Wiſdoms Livery.</l>
               <l>Grace in their hearts: Then I enquiry made</l>
               <l>Where Wiſdoms Palace was: they ſtraight way ſaid,</l>
               <l>"Enter theſe Scriptures, and it will appear,</l>
               <l>"That Wiſdom (whom you ſeek for) dwelleth here.</l>
               <l>"Whoſe glory ('tis ſo great) tongue can't expreſs,</l>
               <l>"When you have entred, you will ſay no leſs</l>
               <l>"She's glorious within, enlightned eyes</l>
               <l>"Do ſee ſuch beauties which they can't but prize</l>
               <l>"She hath one Room all hung with Pearls (you'l ſee)</l>
               <l>"King <hi>Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mons Proverbs</hi> full of dignity.</l>
               <l>"She teaches how to manage every ſtate</l>
               <l>"In which you fall; ſhe'l teach to moderate</l>
               <l>"Proſperity; ſhe'l make affliction bright;</l>
               <l>"She is a cloud by day, and flame by night</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:10"/>"She'l ſhew you ſecret joys, true comforts, and</l>
               <l>"E'relaſting pleaſures, ev'n at Gods right hand.</l>
               <l>Oh! now I have found her Palace, let me wait,</l>
               <l>Till Wiſdom ſhall be pleas'd to ope her Gate.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Of a Proverb.</head>
            <l>Who ſearches oft in ſmal things, worth deſcries</l>
            <l>A pearl is ſmall, and yet of a great price:</l>
            <l>A <hi>Proverb</hi> is a Pearl then, rich, though ſmall,</l>
            <l>But Scriptural moſt precious is of all.</l>
            <l>King <hi>Solomon</hi> hath left Poſterity,</l>
            <l>A rich and everlaſting Legacy;</l>
            <l>A Cabinet of Pearls, which all may take,</l>
            <l>Nor ſhall they yet their fellows poorer make:</l>
            <l>You may perhaps be owner of't, and yet</l>
            <l>I alſo may enjoy the Cabinet.</l>
            <l>Who will not then this Cab'net prize and keep?</l>
            <l>They'r precious Pearls, although they'r in a heap.</l>
            <l>You'l ſay, perhaps, they'r mixt together;—Well,</l>
            <l>Loe here, each Iewel hath it's proper Cell,</l>
            <l>And as your uſe requires, you may repair</l>
            <l>To ſuch a Cell, and have a Jewel there.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:171177:10"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171177:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Solomon</hi>'s PROVERBS, Alphabetically Collected for help of Memory.</head>
            <div n="a" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Adverſity.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. IF thou faint in the day of <hi>Adverſity,</hi> thy ſtrength is but ſmall, <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A Friend loveth at all times, and a Brother is born for <hi>Adverſity,</hi> 17.17.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In the day of Proſperity be joyful; but in the day of <hi>Adverſity</hi> conſider, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Adultery.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Whoſo committeth <hi>Adultery</hi> with a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, lacketh underſtanding: he that doth it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth his own Soul, 6.32.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Such is the way of an <hi>Adulterous</hi> Woman, ſhe eateth, and wipeth her mouth, and ſaith I have done no wickedneſs, 30.20.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:12"/>3. For by means of a whoriſh woman, a man is brought to a piece of bread; and the <hi>Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs</hi> will hunt for the precious life, 6.26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Affliction.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. All the days of the <hi>Afflicted</hi> are evil; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he that is of a merry heart, hath a continua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> feaſt, 15.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Anger.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The diſcretion of man deferreth his <hi>anger</hi> &amp; it is his glory to paſs over tranſgreſſion, 19.11</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that is ſlow to <hi>anger,</hi> is better than th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mighty, 16.32.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Make no friendſhip with an <hi>angry</hi> man; &amp; with a furious man thou ſhalt not go, leſt thou learn his way, 22.24.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. An <hi>angry</hi> man ſtirreth up ſtrife, and a furi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous man aboundeth in tranſgreſſion, 29.22.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He that is ſoon <hi>angry,</hi> dealeth fooliſhly; &amp; a man of wicked devices is hated, 14.17.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Be not haſty in ſpirit to be <hi>angry,</hi> for <hi>ange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> reſteth in the boſom of fools, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A man hath joy by the <hi>anſwer</hi> of his mouth and a word ſpoken in due ſeaſon, how good i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 15.23.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:13"/>2. The heart of the righteous ſtudieth to <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer;</hi> but the mouth of the wicked poureth out evil things, 15.28.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Every man ſhall kiſs his lips that giveth a right <hi>anſwer,</hi> 24.26.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A ſoft <hi>Anſwer</hi> turneth away wrath, but grievous words ſtir up anger, 15.1.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Anſwer</hi> not a fool according to his folly, leſt thou be like unto him, 26.4.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Anſwer</hi> a fool according to his folly, leſt he be wiſe in his own conceit, 26 5.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. He that <hi>anſwereth</hi> a matter before he hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, it is folly and ſhame to him, 18.13.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The preparation of the heart, and <hi>anſwer</hi> of the tongue, is from the Lord, 16.1.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="b" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Babler.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A Serpent will bite without enchantment, and a <hi>Babler</hi> is no better, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Backſlider.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Back-ſlider</hi> in heart ſhall be filled with his own ways; and a good man ſhall be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from himſelf, 14.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Bleſſing.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 The <hi>Bleſſing</hi> of the Lord maketh rich, and he addeth no ſorrow with it, 10.22.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:14"/>2. <hi>Bleſſings</hi> are upon the head of the juſt; but violence covereth the mouth of the wicked, 10.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Blood thirſty.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Blood-thirſty</hi> hate the Upright; but the Juſt ſeek his Soul, 29.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>er.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A <hi>Brother</hi> offended is harder to be won, than a ſtrong City: and their contentions are like the bars of a Caſtle, 18.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Go not into thy <hi>Brothers</hi> houſe in the day of thy Calamity: better is a Neighbour that is near, than a <hi>Brother</hi> that is far off, 27.10.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="c" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Cauſe.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. He that is firſt in his own <hi>Cauſe,</hi> ſeemeth juſt; but his Neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him, 18.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Debate thy <hi>Cauſe</hi> with thy neighbour him ſelf, and diſcover not a ſecret to another, 25.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Open thy mouth for the Dumb in the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of all ſuch as are appointed for deſtruction, 31.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Chaſten.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Deſpiſe not the <hi>Chaſtening</hi> of the Lord, neither be weary of his correction, 3.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Chaſten</hi> thy Son whilſt there is hope, and let not thy ſoul ſpare for his crying, 19.18.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:15"/>3. He that ſpareth his Rod, hateth his Son: but he that loveth him, <hi>chaſtneth</hi> him betimes, 13.24</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Child.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Even a <hi>Child</hi> is known by his doings, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Work be pure, and whether it be right, 20.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Fooliſhneſs is bound in the heart of a <hi>Child;</hi> but the Rod of Correction ſhall drive it far from him, 22.15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Withhold not Correction from thy <hi>Child;</hi> for if thou beateſt him with the Rod, he ſhall not die, 23.13.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A <hi>Child</hi> left to himſelf, bringeth his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſhame, 29.15.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Father of the Righteous ſhall great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rejoyce; and he that begetteth a wiſe, <hi>Child,</hi> ſhall have joy of him, 23.24.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Better is a poor and a wiſe <hi>Child,</hi> than an old and fooliſh King, who will no more be admoniſhed, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.13.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. There is that hath neither <hi>Child</hi> nor Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet hath no end of his labour, nor is his Eye ſatisfied with riches; neither, ſaith he, For whom do I labour, and bereave my Soul of good? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. <hi>Childrens children</hi> are the crown of old Men; and the glory of <hi>Children</hi> are their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, 176.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:16"/>9. If a man beget an hundred <hi>Children,</hi> and live many years, and his Soul be not filled with good, and alſo have no burial; an untimely birth is better than he, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 6.3.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Train up a <hi>Child</hi> in the way he ſhould go, and when he is old he will not depart from it, 22.6.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. I conſidered all the living which walk under the Sun, with the ſecond <hi>Child</hi> that ſhall ſtand up in his ſtead, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>City.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The labour of the fooliſh wearieth every one of them, becauſe he knoweth not how to go to the <hi>City, Eccl.</hi> 10.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Cord.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A three fold <hi>Cord</hi> is not eaſily broken, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 4.12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Crooked.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. That which is <hi>Crooked,</hi> cannot be made ſtraight, and that which is wanting cannot be numbred, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:17"/>
                  <head>Confidence.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Confidence</hi> in an unfaithful man in time of trouble, is like a broken Tooth, and a Foot out of Joynt, 25.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A wiſe man feareth and departeth from evil, but the fool rageth and is <hi>confident,</hi> 14.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Commandment.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Whoſo deſpiſeth the Word, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; but he that feareth the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſhall be rewarded, 13.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that keepeth the <hi>Commandment,</hi> keepeth his own Soul; but he that deſpiſeth his ways, ſhall die, 19.16.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The wiſe in heart will receive <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> but a prating fool ſhall fall, 10.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Comely.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. There be three things that go well, yea, four are <hi>comely</hi> in going; A Lion, which is the ſtrongeſt among Beaſts, and turneth not away for any; a Greyhound, and an He-Goat; alſo a King, againſt whom there is no riſing up, 30.29, 30.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Contentious.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. As Coals are to burning Coals, and Wood to Fire, ſo is a <hi>Contentious</hi> man to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſtrife, 29.12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:18"/>
                  <head>Corn.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He which withholdeth <hi>Corn,</hi> the Peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall curſe him; but the bleſſing ſhall be upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the head of him that ſelleth it, 11.26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Correct.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Correct</hi> thy Son, and he ſhall give thee re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> yea, he ſhall give delight unto thy Soul, 29.17</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Correction</hi> is grievous to him that forſaket<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the way, and he that hateth reproof, ſhall di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 15.10.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A Servant will not be corrected by word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for though he underſtand, he will not anſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 29.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Counſel.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Where no <hi>Counſel</hi> is, the people fall: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in the multitude of <hi>Counſellors</hi> there is ſafety 11.14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Hear <hi>Counſel,</hi> and receive inſtruction, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thou mayſt be wiſe in thy later end, 19.20.</p>
                  <p>Without <hi>Counſel</hi> purpoſes are diſappointe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> but in the multitude of Counſellors they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eſtabliſhed, 15.22.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Every purpoſe is eſtabliſhed by <hi>Counſel</hi> and with good Advice make War, 20.18.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Counſel</hi> in the heart of a man, is like dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Water; but a man of underſtanding will dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it out, 20.5.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. There are many devices in a mans heart but the <hi>Counſel</hi> of the Lord that ſhall ſtand 19.21.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:19"/>7. Ointment and perfume rejoyce the heart: ſo doth the ſweetneſs of a mans friend by hearty <hi>Counſel,</hi> 27.9.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The thoughts of the righteous are right; but the <hi>counſels</hi> of the wicked are deceitful. 12.5.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Deceit is in the hearts of them that imagine evil: but to the <hi>counſellors</hi> of Peace is joy, 12.20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Cover.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He that <hi>Covereth</hi> a tranſgreſſion, ſeeketh love: but he that repeateth a matter ſeparateth very friends, 17.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that covereth his ſins ſhall not proſper; but he who confeſſeth and forſaketh, ſhall find mercy, 28.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Curſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Curſe</hi> of the Lord is in the houſe of the wicked: but he bleſſeth the habitation of the juſt, 3.33.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As the Bird by wandering, as the Swallow by flying; ſo the <hi>Curſe</hi> cauſeleſs ſhall not come, 26 2.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that giveth to the poor ſhall not lack, but he that hideth his eyes ſhall have many <hi>curſes,</hi> 28.27.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="d" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Deceit.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Bread of <hi>deceit</hi> is ſweet to a man; but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his mouth ſhall be fill'd with gravel, 20.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that hateth, diſſembleth with his lips, and layeth up deceit within him, 26.24.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:20"/>3. Whoſe hatred is covered by <hi>deceit,</hi> his wickedneſs ſhall be ſhewed before the whole Congregation, 26.26.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Faithful are the wounds of a Friend; but the kiſſes of an Enemy are <hi>deceitful,</hi> 27.6.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The poor and <hi>deceitful</hi> man meet together: the Lord lightneth both their eyes, 29.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Deſire.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>deſire</hi> accompliſhed is ſweet to the ſoul but it is abomination to fools to depart from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, 13.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>deſire</hi> of a man is his kindneſs: and a poor man is better than a lyar, 19.22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Deſpiſed.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A man ſhall be commended according to his wiſdom: but he that is of a perverſe heart, ſhall be <hi>deſpiſed,</hi> 12.8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that is <hi>deſpiſed,</hi> and hath a ſervant, is better than he that honoreth himſelf, and lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth bread, 12.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Deſtruction.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Before <hi>deſtruction</hi> the heart of man is haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and before honour is humility, 18.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Pride goeth before deſtruction, and a haughty ſpirit before a fall, 16.18.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Hell and <hi>deſtruction</hi> are never full; ſo the eyes of a man are never ſatisfied, 27.20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:21"/>
                  <head>Diligent.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The hand of the <hi>diligent</hi> ſhall bear rule, but the ſlothful ſhall be under tribute, 12.24.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He becometh poor that dealeth with a ſlack hand; but the hand of the diligent maketh rich, 10.4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The ſlothful man roaſteth not what he took in hunting; but the ſubſtance of a <hi>diligent</hi> man is precious, 12.27.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The ſoul of the Sluggard deſireth and hath nothing: but the ſoul of the <hi>diligent</hi> ſhall be made fat, 13.4.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The thoughts of the <hi>diligent</hi> tend only to plentiouſneſs: but of every one that is haſty, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to want, 21.5.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Seeſt thou a man <hi>diligent</hi> in his buſineſs he ſhall ſtand before Kings, he ſhall not ſtand before mean men, 22.29.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. He that diligently ſeeketh good, procureth favour: but he that ſeeketh miſchief, it ſhall come to him, 11.27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Dreams.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. In the multitude of <hi>Dreams</hi> &amp; many words there are alſo divers vanities, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.7.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A <hi>Dream</hi> cometh through multitude of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs: and a fools voice is known by multitude of words, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.3.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="e" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:23"/>
                  <head>Ear.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The heart of the prudent getteth knowledg, and the <hi>Ear</hi> of the wiſe ſeeketh knowledg, 18.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The hearing <hi>Ear,</hi> and the ſeeing Eye, the Lord hath made them both, 20.12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He that turneth away his <hi>Ear</hi> from hearing the Law; even his Prayer ſhall be an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 28.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Eat.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Eat</hi> thou not the bread of him that hath an evil eye: neither deſire his dainty meats, 23.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Earth.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The Profit of the <hi>Earth</hi> is for all, the King himſelf is ſerved by the field, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Enemy.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Rejoice not when thine <hi>Enemy</hi> falleth; let not thy heart be glad when he ſtumbleth, 24.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If thine <hi>Enemy</hi> be hungry, give him bread to eat; and if he be thirſty, give him water to drink, 25.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Envy.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Envy</hi> thou not the Oppreſſor, and chooſe none of his ways, 3.31.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let not thy heart <hi>envy</hi> ſinners: but be thou in the fear of the Lord all the day long, 23.17.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:24"/>3. A ſound heart is the life of the fleſh: but <hi>Envy</hi> is rottenneſs of the Bones, 14.30.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Wrath is cruel, and anger is outragious, but who is able to ſtand before <hi>Envy?</hi> 27.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Evil.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Evil</hi> bow before the Good, and the wicked at the gates of the Righteous, 14.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Evil</hi> men underſtand not judgment; but they that ſeek the Lord, underſtand all things, 28.5</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In the tranſgreſſion of an <hi>evil</hi> man there is a ſnare; but the righteous doth ſing &amp; rejoice, 29.6</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Do not they err that deviſe <hi>Evil?</hi> but mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and truth ſhall be on them that deviſe good 14.22.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Whoſo rewardeth <hi>evil</hi> for good, <hi>evil</hi> ſhal not depart from his houſe, 17.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Eye.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He that winketh with the <hi>Eye,</hi> cauſeth ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row; but a prating fool ſhall fall, 10.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that hath a bountiful <hi>eye,</hi> ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed; for he giveth of his bread to the Poor, 22.9</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>Eye</hi> that mocketh at his Father, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpiſeth to obey his Mother, the Ravens of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Valley ſhall pick it out, 30.17.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. All things are filled with labour, Man can not utter it: the <hi>Eye</hi> is not ſatisfied with ſeeing nor the Ear with hearing, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.8.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:25"/>5. The light of the <hi>Eyes</hi> rejoyceth the heart, and a good report maketh the bones fat, 15.30.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The <hi>Eyes</hi> of the Lord are in every place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the evil and the good, 15.3.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The <hi>Eyes</hi> of the Lord preſerve knowledg, &amp; he overthrows the words of tranſgreſſors, 22.12.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The wiſe mans <hi>Eyes</hi> are in his head; but the Fool walketh in darkneſs, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.14.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Better is the ſight of the <hi>Eyes,</hi> than the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of the deſire, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 6.9.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Be not wiſe in thine own <hi>Eyes:</hi> fear the Lord, and depart from evil, 3.7.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. The way of a fool is right in his own <hi>eyes;</hi> but he that hearkneth to counſel is wiſe, 12.15.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Every way of man is right in his own <hi>eyes;</hi> but the Lord pondereth the hearts, 21.2.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. There are a generation that are pure in their own <hi>eyes,</hi> and yet are not waſhed from their filthineſs, 30.12.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Let thine <hi>eyes</hi> look right on, and let thine <hi>eye-lids</hi> look ſtreight before thee, 4.25.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="f" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Face.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A mans wiſdom maketh his <hi>face</hi> to ſhine, and the boldneſs of his <hi>face</hi> ſhall be changed; <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Father.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Hearken to thy <hi>Father</hi> that begat thee; and deſpiſe not thy Mother when ſhe is old, 23.22.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:26"/>2. Hear ye Children the inſtruction of a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and attend to know underſtanding, 4.1.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A wiſe Son maketh a glad <hi>Father;</hi> but a fooliſh Son is the heavineſs of his Mother, 10.1.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He that begetteth a fool, doth it to his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and the <hi>Father</hi> of a Fool hath no joy, 17.21.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. A wiſe Son heareth his <hi>Fathers</hi> inſtruction, when a fooliſh Son deſpiſeth it: but he that regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth reproof, is prudent, 13.1.—15.5.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. A fooliſh Son is a grief to his <hi>Father;</hi> and bitterneſs to her that bare him, 17.25.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. He that waſteth his <hi>Father,</hi> and chaſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Mother, is a Son that cauſeth ſname, and bringeth reproach, 19.26.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. A fooliſh Son is the calamity of his <hi>Father</hi> 19.13.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Whoſo curſeth his <hi>Father,</hi> or his Mother, his lamp ſhall be put out in obſcure darkneſs, 20.20</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Whoſo robbeth his <hi>Father</hi> or his Mother and ſaith, it is no tranſgreſſion; the ſame is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of a deſtroyer, 28.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Fear.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord prolongeth days: but the years of the wicked ſhall be ſhortned, 10.27.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord is a fountain of life, to depart from the ſnares of death, 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord is the inſtruction o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wiſdom; and before honour is humility, 15.33.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:27"/>4. The <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord is to hate evil: pride, arrogancy, and the evil way, and the froward mouth do I hate, 8.13.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In the <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord is ſtrong confidence, &amp; his children ſhall have a place of refuge, 14.26.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. By mercy and truth iniquity is purged; and by the <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord men part from evil, 16.6.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Better is a little with the <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord, than great treaſure and trouble therewith, 15.16.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord tendeth to life, and he that hath it ſhall abide ſatisfied, he ſhall not be viſited with evil, 19.23.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. By humility and the fear of the Lord are riches and honour and life, 22.4.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. To <hi>fear</hi> God and keep his commandments is the whole duty of man, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.13.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Though the ſinner do evil an hundred times, and his days be prolonged, yet ſurely I know, it ſhall go well with them that <hi>fear</hi> God, which <hi>fear</hi> before him, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.12.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. <hi>Fear thou</hi> the Lord and the King, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not with them that are given to change, 24.21.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Happy is he that <hi>feareth</hi> always; but he that hardneth his heart, ſhall fall into miſchief, 28.14.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. The <hi>fear</hi> of man bringeth a ſnare; but whoſo putteth his truſt in the Lord, he ſhall be ſafe, 29.25,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:28"/>
                  <head>Feaſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A <hi>Feaſt</hi> is made for laughter, and Wine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth merry, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Fire.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Can a man take <hi>Fire</hi> in his boſom, and his cloaths not be burnt, 6.27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Friend.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He that bleſſeth his Friend with a loud voice, riſing early in the morning, it ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a curſe to him, 27.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Fool.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A <hi>Fool</hi> hath no delight in underſtanding, but that his heart may diſcover it ſelf. 18.2.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Fools</hi> make a mock of Sin; but amongſt the righteous there is favour, 14.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A <hi>Fools</hi> lips enter into contention, and his mouth calleth for ſtrokes, 18.6.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A <hi>Fools</hi> wrath is ſoon known, but a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent man covereth ſhame, 12.16.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Even a <hi>Fool</hi> when he holdeth his Peace, is counted wiſe; and he that ſhutteth his lips, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed a man of underſtanding, 17.28.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. It is a ſport to a <hi>Fool</hi> to do miſchief; but a man of underſtanding hath wiſdom, 10.23.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Excellent lips become not a <hi>Fool;</hi> much leſs do lying lips a Prince, 17.7.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:29"/>8. It is an honour for a man to ceaſe from ſtrife but every <hi>fool</hi> will be medling, 20.3.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Every prudent man dealeth with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but a <hi>fool layeth</hi> open his folly, 13.16.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Though thou ſhouldeſt bray a <hi>fool</hi> in a Morte amongſt Wheat with a Peſtle, yet will not his fooliſhneſs depart from him, 27.22.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. A reproof entereth more into a wiſe man, than a hundred ſtripes into a <hi>fool,</hi> 17.10.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Wherefore is there a Price in the hand of a <hi>fool</hi> to get wiſdom, ſeeing he hath no heart to it? 17.16.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Wiſdom is before him that hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; but the eyes of a <hi>Fool</hi> are in the ends of the earth, 17.24.</p>
                  <p n="14">14 In the mouth of the <hi>fooliſh</hi> is a rod of pride, but the lips of the wiſe ſhall preſerve them, 14 3.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. A wiſe mans heart is at his right hand; but a <hi>Fools</hi> heart is at his left, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.2.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Wiſdom reſteth in the heart of him that hath underſtanding; but that which is in the midſt of <hi>Fools</hi> is made known, 14.33.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. Speak not in the ears of a <hi>Fool,</hi> for he will deſpiſe the wiſdom of thy words, 23.9.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. Seeſt thou a man wiſe in his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit? there is more hope of a <hi>Fool</hi> than of him, 26.12</p>
                  <p n="19">19. The Crown of the wiſe is their riches; but the <hi>fooliſhneſs</hi> of <hi>Fools</hi> is folly, 14.24.</p>
                  <p n="20">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:30"/>20. The heart of the wiſe is in the houſe of mourning, but the heart of <hi>fools</hi> is in the houſe of mirth, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.4</p>
                  <p n="21">21. The legs of a lame man are not equal, ſo is a parable in the mouth of <hi>Fools,</hi> 26.7.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. As a thorn goes up in the hand of a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, ſo is a parable in the mouth of <hi>fools,</hi> 26.9.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. As a Dog returneth to his vomit, ſo a <hi>Fool</hi> to his Folly, 26.11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. A ſtone is heavy, and the ſand weighty; but a <hi>fools</hi> wrath is heavier than them both. 27.3.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. Let a Bear robbed of her Whelps meet a man, rather than a <hi>Fool</hi> in his folly, 17.12.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. The words of the wiſe are heard in quiet, more than the cry of him that ruleth among <hi>fools Eccl.</hi> 9.17.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. <hi>Folly</hi> is ſet in great dignity, and the rich ſit in low places, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.6.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. As he that bindeth a ſtone in a ſling, ſo is he that giveth honour to a <hi>Fool,</hi> 26.8.</p>
                  <p n="29">29. A Whip for the Horſe, a Bridle for the Aſs and a Rod for the <hi>Fools</hi> back, 26.3.</p>
                  <p n="30">30. He that troubleth his own houſe, ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Wind, and the <hi>Fool</hi> ſhall be Servant to the wiſe in heart, 11.29.</p>
                  <p n="31">31. Go from the preſence of a <hi>fooliſh</hi> man, when thou perceiveſt not in him the lips of knowledg, 14.7.</p>
                  <p n="32">32. It is better to hear the rebuke of the wiſe, than to hear the Song of <hi>Fools, Eccl.</hi> 7.5.</p>
                  <p n="33">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>33. He that walketh with wiſe men, ſhall be wiſe; but a companion of <hi>Fools</hi> ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 13.20.</p>
                  <p n="34">34. He that ſendeth a meſſage by the hand of a <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ool,</hi> cuts off the feet, and drinks dammage, 26.6.</p>
                  <p n="35">35. Dead flies cauſe the Oyntment of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary to ſend forth a ſtinking ſavour, ſo doth a little <hi>folly</hi> him that is in reputation for wiſdom and honour, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.1.</p>
                  <p n="36">36. The folly of <hi>fools</hi> is deceit, 14.8.</p>
                  <p n="37">37. The great God that formeth all things, both rewardeth the <hi>Fool,</hi> and rewardeth the tranſgreſſors, 26.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Friend.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A man that hath <hi>Friends</hi> muſt ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf friendly: there is a <hi>Friend</hi> that ſticketh cloſer than a Brother, 18.24.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Iron ſharpneth Iron; ſo a man ſharpneth the countenance of his <hi>Friend,</hi> 27 17.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He that loves pureneſs of heart, for the grace of his lips the King ſhall be his <hi>friend,</hi> 22.11.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Thine own <hi>Friend</hi> and thy Fathers <hi>Friend</hi> forſake not, 27.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Froward.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A naughty perſon, a wicked man, walketh with a <hi>froward</hi> mouth, 6.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that hath a <hi>froward</hi> heart, findeth no good, 17.20.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:32"/>3 A <hi>froward</hi> man ſoweth ſtrife, and a whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſeparateth chief friends, 16.28.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Thorns and ſnares are in the way of the <hi>froward;</hi> he that doth keep his ſoul ſhall be far from them, 22.5.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The <hi>froward</hi> is an abomination to the Lord; but his ſecret is with the righteous, 3.32.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The mouth of the juſt brings forth wiſdom, but the <hi>froward</hi> tongue ſhall be cut out, 10.31.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Put away from thee the <hi>froward</hi> mouth, and perverſe lips put far from thee, 4.24.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="g" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Gift.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A mans <hi>Gift</hi> maketh room for him, and bringeth him before great men, 18.16.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A <hi>Gift</hi> in ſecret pacifieth anger; and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the boſom ſtrong wrath, 21.14.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A <hi>Gift</hi> is a precious ſtone in the eyes of him that hath it; whitherſoever it turneth it proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, 17.8.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A wicked man taketh a <hi>Gift</hi> out of his boſom to pervert the ways of judgment, 17.23.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He that is greedy of gain troubleth his own houſe; but he that hateth <hi>Gifts</hi> ſhall live, 15.27</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Whoſo boaſteth of a falſe <hi>Gift,</hi> is like clouds and wind without rain, 25.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:33"/>
                  <head>Goods.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. When <hi>goods</hi> encreaſe, they are encreaſed that eat them: and what good is there to the owners thereof, ſaving the beholding them with their eyes? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Grave.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Whatſoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy might; for there is no work, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, nor wiſdom, nor knowledge in the <hi>Grave</hi> whither thou goeſt, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There are three things that are never ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; yea four things ſay not, It is enough: The <hi>Grave,</hi> and the barren Womb, the earth that is not filled with water, and the Fire that ſaith not, It is enough, 30.15, 16.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="h" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. If thou haſt done fooliſhly in lifting up thy ſelf; or if thou haſt thought evil, lay thy <hi>hand</hi> upon thy mouth, 30.32.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Kings heart is in the <hi>hand</hi> of the Lord as the Rivers of Water; he turnerh it whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he will, 21.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Haſte.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Seeſt thou a man <hi>haſty</hi> in his words? there is more hope of a fool than of him, 29.20.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that is ſlow to wrath is of great under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: but he that is <hi>haſty</hi> of ſpirit exalteth folly, 14.19,</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:34"/>3. Go not forth <hi>haſtily</hi> to ſtrive, leſt thou know not what to do in the end thereof, when thy neighbor hath put thee to ſhame, 25.8.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be <hi>haſty</hi> to utter any thing before God: for he is in Heaven and thou upon Earth, therefore let thy words be few, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Hatred.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Hatred</hi> ſtirreth up ſtrifes, but love covereth all ſins, 10.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that hideth <hi>hatred</hi> with lying lips; he that uttereth a ſlander, is a fool, 10.18.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Better is a dinner of herbs where love is, than a ſtalled Ox, and <hi>hatred</hi> therewith, 15.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Head.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Let thy garments be always white, and let thy <hi>head</hi> want no oyntment, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Glory of young men is their ſtrength: and the beauty of old men is the gray <hi>head,</hi> 20.29.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The hoary <hi>head</hi> is a Crown of glory, if it be found in the way of righteouſneſs, 16.31.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Heart.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. My ſon give me thy heart, and let thine eyes obſerve thy ways, 23.26.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A mans <hi>heart</hi> deviſeth his way, but the Lord directeth his ſteps, 16.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:35"/>3. A mans <hi>heart</hi> knoweth his own bitterneſs, and a ſtranger doth not intermedle with his joy, 14.10.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A merry <hi>heart</hi> maketh a cheerful counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, 15.13.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. A merry <hi>heart</hi> doth good, like a medicine; but a broken ſpirit dryeth the bones, 17.22.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. It is better to go to the houſe of mourning than to the houſe of feaſting; for that is the end of all men, &amp; the living will lay it to <hi>heart, Ec.</hi> 7.2.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. As he that takes away a garment in cold weather, and as Vinegar upon Nitre: ſo is he that ſingeth ſongs to an heavy <hi>heart,</hi> 25.20.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The fooliſhneſs of man perverteth his way, and his <hi>heart</hi> fretteth againſt the Lord, 19.3.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. The heart of him that hath underſtanding ſeeketh knowledge; but the mouth of fools feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on fooliſhneſs, 15.14.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. The tongue of the juſt is as choice ſilver: the <hi>heart</hi> of the wicked is little worth, 10.20.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. He that truſteth in his own <hi>heart,</hi> is a fool; whoſo walketh wiſely, ſhall be delivered, 28.26.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. The heaven for height, the earth for depth and the <hi>heart</hi> of Kings is unſearchable, 15.3.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. The fining-pot for ſilver, and the furnace for gold, but the Lord tryeth the <hi>hearts,</hi> 17.3.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Hell and deſtruction are before the Lord, how much more the <hi>hearts</hi> of the children of men, 15.11.</p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:36"/>15. As in water face anſwereth face, ſo the <hi>heart</hi> of man to man, 27.19.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Who can ſay, I have made my <hi>heart</hi> clean I am free from my ſin? 20.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Honey.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Haſt thou found <hi>Honey?</hi> eat that which is ſufficient for thee, leſt thou be filled therewith and vomit it, 25.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Honour.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He that followeth after righteouſneſs and mercy, findeth life, righteouſneſs &amp; <hi>honor,</hi> 21.21</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A gracious woman retaineth <hi>honour,</hi> and ſtrong men retain riches, 11.16.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A mans Pride ſhall bring him low; but <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour</hi> ſhall uphold the humble ſpirit, 29.23.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whoſo keepeth the fig-tree, ſhall eat th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fruit thereof: ſo he that waiteth on his Maſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall be <hi>honoured,</hi> 27.18.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In the multitude of people is the Kings <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour;</hi> but in the want of people is the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction of the Prince, 14.28.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. As Snow in ſummer, and rain in harveſt ſo <hi>honour</hi> is not ſeemly for a fool, 26.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Hope.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Hope</hi> deferred makes the heart ſick, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> when the deſire cometh, it is a tree of life, 13.12</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:37"/>2. For to him that is joyned to all the living there is <hi>hope;</hi> for a living Dog is better than a dead Lyon, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>hope</hi> of the righteous ſhall be gladneſs, but the expectation of the wicked ſhall periſh, 10.28.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. When a wicked man dyeth, his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall periſh, and the <hi>hope</hi> of the unjuſt man periſheth, 11.7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Houſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Houſe</hi> of the wicked ſhall be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, but the Tabernacle of the upright ſhall flouriſh, 14.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Lord will deſtroy the <hi>Houſe</hi> of the proud, but he will eſtabliſh the border of the Widow, 15.25.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The wicked are overthrown, and are not but the <hi>Houſe</hi> of the righteous ſhall ſtand, 12.7.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In the <hi>Houſe</hi> of the righteous is much trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; but in the revenues of the wicked is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, 15.6.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Through Wiſdom is a <hi>Houſe</hi> builded, and by underſtanding it is eſtabliſhed, 24.3.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Withdraw thy foot from thy Neighbours <hi>Houſe,</hi> leſt he be weary of thee, and ſo hate thee, 25.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:38"/>
                  <head>Humble.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Better it is to be of an <hi>humble</hi> ſpirit with the lowly, than to divide the ſpoyl with the proud, 16.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A mans pride ſhall bring him low, but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſhall uphold the humble in ſpirit, 29.23.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Do this now my ſon, &amp; deliver thy ſelf, when thou art come into the hand of thy friend; go <hi>humble</hi> thy ſelf, and make ſure thy friend, 6.3.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. When men are caſt down, then thou ſhalt ſay, there is lifting up, and he ſhall ſave the <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> perſon, <hi>Job</hi> 22.29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Hunger.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Slothfulneſs caſteth into a deep ſleep, and an idle ſoul ſhall ſuffer <hi>hunger,</hi> 19.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Men do not deſpiſe a thief, if he ſteal to ſatisfie his ſoul, when he is <hi>hungry,</hi> 6.30.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The full Soul loatheth a honey-comb: but to the <hi>hungry</hi> ſoul every bitter thing is ſweet, 27.7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Hypocrite.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. An <hi>Hypocrite</hi> with his mouth deſtroyeth his neighbour: but through knowledge ſhall the juſt be delivered, 11.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The triumphing of the wicked is ſhort, &amp; the joy of the <hi>hypocrite</hi> but for a moment, <hi>Job</hi> 20.5.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What is the hope of a <hi>Hypocrite</hi> though he hath gained, when God taketh away his ſoul? <hi>Job</hi> 27.8,</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:40"/>4. That the <hi>Hypocrite</hi> reign not, leſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be inſnared, <hi>Job</hi> 34.30.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="i" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Increaſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Honour the Lord with thy ſubſtance, and the firſt fruits of all thine <hi>Increaſe,</hi> 3.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There is that ſcattereth, and yet <hi>increaſeth;</hi> and there is that withholdeth more than is meet but it tendeth to poverty, 11.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Inheritance.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Wiſdom is good with an <hi>Inheritance,</hi> and by it there is profit to them that ſee the Sun, <hi>Ec.</hi> 7.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A good man leaveth an <hi>Inheritance</hi> to his childrens children, and the wealth of the ſinner is laid up for the juſt, 13.22.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. An <hi>Inheritance</hi> may be gotten haſtily at the beginning, but the end thereof ſhall not be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; 20.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Inſtruction.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Apply thy heart to <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> and thine ears to the words of knowledge, 23.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Hear <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> and be wiſe, and refuſe it not, 8.33.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Whoſo loveth <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> loveth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but he that hateth reproof is bruitiſh, 21.1</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He is in the way of life that keepeth <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> but he that refuſeth reproof, erreth, 10.17.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:41"/>5. The Commandment is a Lamp and the Law is light; and reproofs of <hi>Inſtruction</hi> are the ways of life; 6.23.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Give <hi>Inſtruction</hi> to a wiſe man, and he will be yet wiſer; teach a juſt man, and he will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in learning, 9.9.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. He that refuſeth <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> deſpiſeth his own ſoul: but he that heareth reproof, getteth underſtanding; 15.32.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Poverty and ſhame ſhall be to him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> but he that regardeth reproof ſhall be honoured, 13.18.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Take faſt hold of <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> let her not go, keep her; for ſhe is thy life, 4.13.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Ceaſe my Son to hear the <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> that cauſeth to err from the words of knowledge, 19 27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Integrity.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Integrity</hi> of the upright ſhall guide them, but the perverſneſs of tranſgreſſors ſhall deſtroy them, 11.3.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Better is the poor that walketh in his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity,</hi> than he that is perverſe in his lips, and is a fool, 19.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Iudgment.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The King by <hi>Judgment</hi> eſtabliſhes the land but he that receiveth gifts overthrows it, 29.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Many ſeek the Rulers favour: but every mans <hi>Judgment</hi> cometh of the Lord, 29.26.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:42"/>3. Much Food is in the Tillage of the poor: but there is that is deſtroyed for want of <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 13.23</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whoſo keepeth the Commandment, ſhall feel no evil thing: and a wiſe mans heart diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth both time and <hi>judgment, Eccl.</hi> 8.5.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Becauſe to every purpoſe there is a time and <hi>judgment;</hi> therefore the miſery of a man is great upon him, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.6.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The robbery of the wicked ſhall deſtroy them, becauſe they refuſe to do <hi>judgment,</hi> 21.7.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Judgments are prepared for ſcorners, and ſtripes for the back of fools, 19.29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Iuſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. It is joy to the <hi>Juſt</hi> to do judgment, but deſtruction ſhall be to the workers of iniquity, 21.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>juſt</hi> man walketh in his integrity; his children are bleſſed after him, 20.7.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The path of the <hi>Juſt</hi> is as a ſhining light, that ſhineth more and more unto the perfect day, 4.18.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The memory of the <hi>Juſt</hi> is bleſſed; but the name of the wicked ſhall rot, 10.7.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The wicked is ſnared by the tranſgreſſion of his Lips: but the <hi>Juſt</hi> ſhall come out of trouble, 12.13.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. A <hi>Juſt</hi> man falleth ſeven times, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth up again: but the wicked ſhall fall into miſchief, 24.16.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:43"/>7. He that <hi>juſtifieth</hi> the Wicked, and he that condemneth the <hi>Juſt,</hi> even both are an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Lord, 17.15.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. To puniſh the <hi>Juſt</hi> is not good, nor to ſtrike Princes for equity, 17.26.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="k" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>King.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A divine ſentence is in the lips of <hi>Kings,</hi> his mouth tranſgreſſeth not in judgment, 16.10</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is an abomination to Kings to commit wickedneſs, for the Throne is eſtabliſhed by righteouſneſs, 16.12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Righteous lips are the delight of <hi>Kings,</hi> &amp; they love him that ſpeaketh right, 16 13.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A <hi>King</hi> that ſitteth in the Throne of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſcatters away all evil with his eyes, 20.8.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. A wiſe <hi>King</hi> ſcattereth the Wicked, and bringeth the wheel over them, 20.26.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. It is the glory of God to conceal a thing; but the honour of a <hi>King</hi> to ſearch out the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 25.2.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Where the Word of a <hi>King</hi> is, there is power; and who may ſay unto a <hi>King,</hi> What doſt thou? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Job.</hi> 34.18.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The wrath of a <hi>King</hi> is as Meſſengers of death, but a wiſe man will pacifie it, 16.14.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. The <hi>Kings</hi> wrath is as the roaring of a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but his favour is as dew upon the graſs, 19.12.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:44"/>10. In the light of the <hi>Kings</hi> countenance is Life, and his Favour is as the cloud of the latter Rain, 16.15.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. The <hi>King</hi> that faithfully judgeth the poor his throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed for ever, 29.14</p>
                  <p n="12">12. It is not for <hi>Kings</hi> to drink Wine, nor for Princes ſtrong drink; leſt they drink and forget the Law, and pervert the judgment of any of the afflicted, 31.4, 5.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Wo to thee, O Land, when thy <hi>King</hi> is a child, and thy Princes eat in the morning, <hi>Ec.</hi> 10.16.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Take away the wicked from before the <hi>King,</hi> and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſs, 25.5.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Curſe not the <hi>King,</hi> no not in thy thought, and curſe not the rich in thy Bed-chamber; for a Bird of the Air ſhall carry the voice, and that which hath wings ſhall tell the matter, <hi>Ec.</hi> 10.20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Knowledge.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. There is Gold, and a multitude of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, but the Lips of <hi>Knowledge</hi> are a precious Jewel, 20.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Receive my Inſtruction, and not Silver; and <hi>Knowledge</hi> rather than choice Gold, 8.10.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the Soul be without <hi>Knowledge,</hi> it is not good; and he that haſteth with his feet, ſinneth, 19.2.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:45"/>4. He that hath <hi>Knowledge,</hi> ſpareth his words; and a man of underſtanding is of an excellent ſpirit, 17.27.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Wiſdom is a defence, and Money is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; but the excellency of <hi>Knowledge</hi> is, that Wiſdom giveth life to them that have it, Ec. 7.12.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="l" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Labour.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. In all <hi>Labour</hi> there is profit; but the talk of the lips tendeth to poverty, 14.23.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that <hi>laboureth, laboureth</hi> for himſelf, for his mouth craveth it of him, 15.26.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. All the <hi>Labour</hi> of man is for his mouth; yet the appetite is not filled. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 6 7.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Wealth gotten by vanity, ſhall be dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; but he that gathereth by <hi>Labour,</hi> ſhall increaſe, 13.11.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. All things are full of <hi>Labour,</hi> Man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not utter it, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.8.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. There is a man whoſe <hi>Labour</hi> is in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and in knowledge, and in equity; yet to a man that hath not <hi>laboured</hi> therein, ſhall he leave it for his portion, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.21.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. There is nothing better for a man, than that he ſhould eat and drink, and that he ſhould make his Soul enjoy good in his <hi>Labour, Eccl.</hi> 2.24.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:46"/>8. Every man alſo to whom God hath given Riches, and Wealth, and given him power to eat thereof, and to take his portion, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in his <hi>Labour;</hi> this is the gift of God, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.19.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. What hath man of all his <hi>Labour,</hi> and of the vexation of his heart, wherein he hath la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured under the Sun? <hi>Ec.</hi> 2.22.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. As he ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> forth of his Mothers Womb, naked ſhall he return to go as he came, and ſhall take nothing of his <hi>Labour</hi> which he may carry away in his hand, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.15.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. And this is alſo a ſore evil; that in all points as he came, ſo ſhall he go, and what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit hath he that hath <hi>laboured</hi> for the wind? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Land.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He that tilleth his <hi>Land</hi> ſhall have plenty of Bread; but he that followeth after vain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, is void of underſtanding, and ſhall have poverty enough, 28, 19. <hi>with</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Remove not the antient <hi>Land-mark</hi> which thy Fathers have ſet, 22.28.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. For the tranſgreſſion of a <hi>Land,</hi> many are the Princes thereof; but by a man of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and knowledge, the ſtate thereof ſhall be prolonged, 28.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:47"/>
                  <head>Laughter.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Even in <hi>Laughter</hi> the heart is ſorrowful; and the end of that mirth is heavineſs, 14.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I ſaid of <hi>Laughter,</hi> it is mad; and of mirth, what doth it? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Sorrow is better than <hi>Laughter,</hi> for by the ſadneſs of the countenance the Heart is made better, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.3.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A time to weep, and a time to <hi>laugh,</hi> a time to mourn, and a time to dance, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.4.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. As the cracklings of Thorns under a Pot, ſo is the <hi>Laughter</hi> of a fool, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.6.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. A Feaſt is made for <hi>Laughter,</hi> and Wine maketh merry; but Money anſwereth all things, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Law.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Law</hi> of the Wiſe is a fountain of life, to depart from the ſnares of death, 13.14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Where there is no viſion, the people pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; but he that keepeth the <hi>Law,</hi> happy is he, 29, 18.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They that forſake the <hi>Law,</hi> praiſe the wicked; but ſuch as keep the <hi>Law</hi> contend with them, 28.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Liberal.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Liberal</hi> ſoul ſhall be made fat; and he that watereth, ſhall be watered alſo himſelf, 11.25.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:48"/>
                  <head>Lips</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Lips</hi> of the righteous feed many; but fools dye for want of wiſdom, 10.21.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Lips</hi> of the righteous know what is acceptable; but the mouth of the wicked ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth frowardneſs, 10.32.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>Lips</hi> of the wiſe diſperſe knowledge; but the heart of the fooliſh doth not ſo, 15.7.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In the <hi>Lips</hi> of him that hath underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wiſdom is found; but a rod is for the back of him that is void of underſtanding, 10.13.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The words of a wiſe mans mouth are Gracious; but the <hi>Lips</hi> of a fool will ſwallow up himſelf, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.12.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Burning <hi>Lips,</hi> and a wicked Heart, are like a potſheard covered with ſilver droſs, 26.23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Lot.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Lot</hi> is caſt into the lap; but the whole diſpoſing thereof is of the Lord 16.33.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Lot</hi> cauſeth contention to ceaſe, and parteth between the mighty, 18.18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Lye.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A wicked doer giveth heed to falſe Lips; and a <hi>Lyer</hi> giveth ear to a naughty tongue, 17.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A <hi>lying</hi> tongue hateth thoſe that are afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it, and a flattering mouth worketh ruine, 26.28.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:49"/>3. A proud look and and a <hi>lying</hi> Tongue, the Lord hates, 6.17.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He that ſpeaketh <hi>lyes,</hi> ſhall not eſcape. 19.5, 6.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The <hi>lying</hi> Tongue is but for a moment, 12.19.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Lying</hi> Lips are an abomination to the Lord; but they that deal truly, are his delight, 12.22.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. A righteous man hateth <hi>lying;</hi> but a wicked man is loathſome, and cometh to ſhame, 13.5.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The getting of Treaſures by a <hi>lying</hi> Tongue, is vanity toſſed to and fro of them that ſeek death; 21.6.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Remove far from me vanity and <hi>lyes,</hi> 30.8.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="m" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Mercy.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Mercy,</hi> and Truth preſerve the King, and his Throne is upholden in <hi>Mercy,</hi> 20.28.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Merciful</hi> man doth good to his ſoul; but he that is cruel, troubleth his own fleſh, 11.17.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He that deſpiſeth his neighbour, ſinneth; but he that hath <hi>Mercy</hi> on the poor, happy is he, 14.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Meſſenger.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A wicked <hi>Meſſenger</hi> falleth into miſchief, but a faithful Ambaſſador is health; 13.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:50"/>2. As the cold of Snow in the time of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, ſo is a faithful <hi>Meſſenger</hi> to them that ſend him; for he refreſheth the ſoul of his Maſters, 25.13.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. An evil man ſeeketh only rebellion; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a cruel <hi>Meſſenger</hi> ſhall be ſent againſt him, 17.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Money.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Money</hi> anſwereth all things, <hi>Ecc.</hi> 10.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Morrow.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Boaſt not thy ſelf of to <hi>Morrow,</hi> for thou knoweſt not what a day may bring forth, 27.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Mouth.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A man ſhall eat good by the fruit of his <hi>Mouth;</hi> but the ſoul of the tranſgreſſors ſhall eat violence, chap. 13.2.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A man ſhall be ſatisfied with good by the fruit of his <hi>Mouth;</hi> and the recompence of a mans hands ſhall be rendred to him, 12.14.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A mans Belly ſhall be ſatisfied with the fruit of his <hi>Mouth;</hi> and with the increaſe of his Lips ſhall be filled, 18.20.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He that keepeth his <hi>Mouth,</hi> keepeth his Life; but he that openeth wide his Lips, ſhall have deſtruction, 13.3.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. By the Bleſſing of the Upright the City is exalted; but 'tis overthrown by the <hi>Mouth</hi> of the wicked, 11.11.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:51"/>6. The words of the wicked are to lie in wait for blood; but the <hi>Mouth</hi> of the upright ſhall deliver them, 12.6.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Thou art ſnared by the words of thy <hi>mouth;</hi> thou art taken by the words of thy <hi>mouth,</hi> 6.2.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. A fools <hi>Mouth</hi> is his deſtruction, and his Lips are the ſnare of his Soul, 18.7.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Suffer not thy <hi>Mouth</hi> to cauſe thy fleſh to ſin, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.6.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="n" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Name.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A good <hi>Name</hi> is rather to be choſen than great Riches; and loving Favour rather than Silver and Gold, 22.1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A good <hi>Name</hi> is better than precious Oyntment; and the day of Death is better than the day of ones Birth, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.1.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>Name</hi> of the Lord is a ſtrong Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; the Righteous runneth into it and is ſafe, 18.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Naught.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. It is <hi>naught,</hi> it is <hi>naught,</hi> ſaith the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; but when he is gone his way, then he boaſteth, 20.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Neighbour.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Better is a <hi>Neighbour</hi> that is near, than a Brother that is far off, 27.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that is void of wiſdom, deſpiſeth his <hi>Neighbour,</hi> but a man of underſtanding holdeth his peace, 11.12.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:52"/>3. Say not unto thy <hi>Neighbour,</hi> Go and come again, and to morrow I will give; when thou haſt it by thee, 3.28.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A man that flattereth with his <hi>Neighbour,</hi> ſpreadeth a Net for his feet, 29.5.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. As a mad man who caſteth Firebrands, Arrows, and Death; ſo is the man that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth his <hi>Neighbour,</hi> and ſaith, Am I not in ſport? 26.18, 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Net</head>
                  <p n="1">1. In vain the <hi>Net</hi> is ſpread in the ſight of any Bird, 1.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>News.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. As cold water to a thirſty ſoul, ſo is good <hi>News</hi> from a far Countrey, 25.25.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="o" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Oppreſsion.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He that <hi>oppreſſeth</hi> the poor, <hi>reproacheth</hi> his Maker: but he that honoureth him, hath mercy on the poor, 14 31.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A poor man that <hi>oppreſſeth</hi> the poor, is like a ſweeping rain which leaveth no food, 28.3.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> maketh a wiſe man mad, and a gift deſtroyeth the heart, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.7.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Prince that wanteth underſtanding is alſo a great <hi>Oppreſſor</hi> but he that hateth covetouſneſs ſhall prolong his days, 28.19.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:53"/>5. I conſidered all the <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> that are done under the Sun; and behold the tears of ſuch as were <hi>Oppreſſed,</hi> and they had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter; and on the ſide of the <hi>Oppreſſor</hi> there was power. Wherefore I praiſed the dead which are already dead, more than the living which are yet alive, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.1, 2.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. If thou ſeeſt the <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> of the poor, and violent perverting of judgment and juſtice in a Province, marvel not at the matter; for he that is higher than the higheſt regardeth, and there be higher than they, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Ox.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Where no <hi>Oxen</hi> are, the Crib is clean; but much increaſe is by the ſtrength of the <hi>Ox.</hi> 14.4.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="p" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Paſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. That which hath been, is now; and that which is to be, hath already been, and God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth that which is <hi>paſt, Eccl.</hi> 3.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Pit.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Whoſo diggeth a <hi>Pit</hi> ſhall fall therein; and he that rolleth a ſtone, it will return upon him, 26.27.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whoſo cauſeth the righteous to go aſtray in evil ways, he ſhall fall himſelf into his own <hi>Pit;</hi> but the upright ſhall have good things in poſſeſſion; 28.10.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:54"/>3. He that diggeth a <hi>Pit</hi> ſhall fall into it; and whoſo breaketh a Hedge, a Serpent ſhall bite him, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Poor.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He that loveth pleaſure ſhall be a poor man; he that loveth Wine and Oyl ſhall not be rich, 21.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There is that withholdeth more than is meet, and it tendeth to <hi>poverty,</hi> 11.24.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He that followeth after vain perſons, ſhall have <hi>poverty</hi> enough, 28.19.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Be not among Wine-bibbers, amongſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otous eaters of fleſh; for the Drunkard and the Glutton ſhall come to <hi>poverty;</hi> and drowſineſs ſhall cloath a man with Rags, 23.20, 21.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Love not ſleep leſt thou come to <hi>poverty;</hi> open thine eyes, and thou ſhalt be ſatisfied with bread, 20.13.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Yet a little ſleep, a little ſlumber, a little folding of the hands to ſleep; ſo ſhall thy <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty</hi> come as one that travelleth; and thy want as an armed man, 24.33, 34.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. He that haſteneth to be rich, hath an evil eye, and conſidereth not that <hi>poverty</hi> ſhall come upon him, 28.22.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The ranſom of a mans life are his riches; but the poor heareth not rebuke, 13.8.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:55"/>9. There is that maketh himſelf rich, yet hath nothing; there is that maketh himſelf <hi>poor,</hi> yet hath great riches, 13.7.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. The deſire of a man is his kindneſs; and a <hi>poor</hi> man is better than a lyar, 19.22.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Better is the <hi>poor</hi> that walketh in his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs, than he that is perverſe in his ways, though he be rich, 28.6.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Wealth maketh many friends; but the <hi>poor</hi> is ſeparated from his neighbour: 19.4.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. All the brethren of the <hi>poor</hi> do hate him; how much more do his friends go far from him. He purſueth them with words, yet they are wanting to him, 19.7.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. The <hi>poor</hi> is hated even of his neighbour, 14.20.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. The rich ruleth over the <hi>poor,</hi> and the borrower is ſervant to the lender, 22.7.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. The <hi>poor</hi> uſeth intreaty; but the rich anſwereth roughly, 18.23.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. There are a generation whoſe Teeth are as ſwords, their jaw-teeth as knives, to devour the <hi>poor</hi> from the earth, and the needy from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men. 30.14.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. Rob not the <hi>poor</hi> becauſe he is <hi>poor;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oppreſs the afflicted in the gate, 22.22.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. He that oppreſſeth the <hi>poor</hi> to increaſe his riches, and he that giveth to the rich, ſhall ſurely come to want, 22.16.</p>
                  <p n="20">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:56"/>20. Whoſo mocketh the poor, reproacheth his Maker; and he that is glad at calamities, ſhall not be unpuniſhed, 17.5.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. The rich and <hi>poor</hi> meet together; the Lord is the maker of them both, 22.2.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. He that hath pity on the <hi>poor,</hi> lendeth to the Lord; and that which he hath given, will he pay again, 19.17.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. The righteous conſidereth the cauſe of the <hi>poor;</hi> but the wicked regardeth not to know it, 29.7.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. He that hath a bounti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l eye ſhall be bleſſed; for he giveth of his Bread to the <hi>poor,</hi> 22 9.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. Whoſo ſtoppeth his ear at the cry of the <hi>poor,</hi> he alſo ſhall cry himſelf and not be heard; 21.13.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. Open thy mouth, judge righteouſly, plead the cauſe of the <hi>poor</hi> and needy, 31.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Portion.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Give a <hi>portion</hi> to ſeven, and alſo to eight; for thou knoweſt not what evil ſhall come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Praiſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1, As the Fining-pot for Silver, and the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace for Gold, ſo is a man to his praiſe, 27.21.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let another man <hi>praiſe</hi> thee, and not thy own mouth; a ſtranger, and not thy own lips, 27.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:57"/>
                  <head>Pride.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Only by <hi>pride</hi> cometh correction, but with the well-adviſed is wiſdom, 13.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. When <hi>pride</hi> cometh, then cometh ſhame; but with the lowly is wiſdom, 11.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. An high look, a <hi>proud</hi> heart, and the plowing of the wicked is ſin. 21.4.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Every one that is proud in heart, is an abomination to the Lord: though hand joyn in hand, he ſhall not be unpuniſhed, 16.5.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He that is of a <hi>proud</hi> heart, ſtirreth up ſtrife; but he that putteth his truſt in the Lord, ſhall be made fat, 28.25.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Better is the end of a thing than the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning thereof; and the patient in ſpirit than the <hi>proud</hi> in ſpirit, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.8.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Proud</hi> and haughty ſcorner is his name, who dealeth in proud wrath, 21.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Prudent.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A <hi>Prudent</hi> man concealeth knowledge, but the heart of fools proclaimeth fooliſhneſs, 12.23.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The wiſdom of the <hi>Prudent</hi> is to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his way, 14.8.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The wiſe in heart ſhall be called <hi>Prudent;</hi> and the ſweetneſs of the Lips increaſeth Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 16.21.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A <hi>Prudent</hi> man foreſeeth the evil, and hideth himſelf; but the ſimple paſs on and are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 22.3.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:58"/>5. The ſimple believeth every word, but the <hi>prudent</hi> looketh well to his going, 14.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Prince.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Delight is not ſeemly for a fool; much leſs for a ſervant to rule over a <hi>Prince,</hi> 19.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Many will intreat the favour of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and every man is a friend to him that giveth gifts, 19.6.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By long forbearing is a <hi>Prince</hi> perſwaded, 25.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Proclaim.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Moſt men will proclaim every one his own goodneſs; but a faithful man, who can find? 20.6.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="q" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Quiet.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Whoſo hearkens to wiſdom ſhall dwell ſafely, and ſhall be <hi>quiet</hi> from fear of evil. 1.33.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Better is a dry morſel, and <hi>quietneſs</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, than a houſe full of ſacrifices with ſtrife, 17.1.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Better is a handful with <hi>quietneſs,</hi> than both the hands full with travel and vexation of ſpirit, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.6.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="r" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Rebuke.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Open <hi>Rebuke</hi> is better than ſecret love, 27.5.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A ſcorner heareth not <hi>Rebuke,</hi> 13.1.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:59"/>3. To them that <hi>rebuke</hi> the wicked ſhall be delight; and a good bieſſing ſhall come upon them, 24.25.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He that reproveth a ſcorner, getteth to himſelf ſhame; and he that <hi>rebuketh</hi> a wicked man, getteth himſelf a blot, 9.7.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He that <hi>rebuketh</hi> a man, afterwards ſhall find more favour, than he that flattereth with with his tongue, 28.23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Recompence.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Say not I will <hi>recompence</hi> evil; but wait on the Lord and he ſhall ſave thee, 20.22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Reprover.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. As an Ear-ring of Gold, and an ornament of fine Gold; ſo is a wiſe <hi>Reprover</hi> to an obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Ear, 25.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Rod and <hi>Reproof</hi> give wiſdom, 29.15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Reproofs</hi> of inſtruction are the way of life, 6.23.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He that heareth <hi>Reproof,</hi> getteth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, 15.32.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The ear that heareth the <hi>reproof</hi> of life; abideth among the wiſe, 15.31.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Reprove</hi> one that hath underſtanding, and he will underſtand knowledge, 19.25.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Reprove</hi> not a ſcorner leſt he hate thee; rebuke a wiſe man, and he will love thee, 9.8.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. He that refuſeth <hi>reproof</hi> erreth, 10.17.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:60"/>9. He that hateth <hi>reproof</hi> is brutiſh, and ſhall die, 12.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.10.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. He that being often <hi>reproved</hi> hardneth his neck; ſhall ſuddainly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy, 29.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Reſpect.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. It is not good to have <hi>Reſpect</hi> of perſons in judgment, 24 23.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To have <hi>Reſpect</hi> of perſons, is not good: for, for a piece of bread that man will tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, 28.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Rich.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Labour not to be <hi>rich;</hi> ceaſe from thy own underſtanding, 23.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Riches</hi> profit not in the day of wrath; but righteouſneſs delivereth from death, 11.4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Wilt thou ſet thine eyes upon that which is not? for <hi>Riches</hi> certainly make themſelves wings; they flee away as an Eagle towards Heaven, 23.5.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Riches</hi> are not for ever, and doth the Crown endure to every generation? 27.24.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The ſleep of a labouring man is ſweet; whether he eat little or much: but the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the <hi>Rich</hi> will not ſuffer him to ſleep, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.12.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. A faithful man ſhall abound with bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; but he that maketh haſte to be <hi>rich,</hi> ſhall not be innocent, 28.20.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:61"/>7. He that truſteth in his <hi>Riches</hi> ſhall fall; but the righteous ſhall flouriſh as a branch, 11.28.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The <hi>Rich</hi> man's wealth is his ſtrong Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and as an high wall in his own conceit. The deſtruction of the poor is their poverty, 18.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.15.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. The <hi>Rich</hi> hath many friends, 14.20.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Give me neither Poverty nor <hi>Riches:</hi> feed me with food convenient for me, 30.8.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. There is a ſore evil that I have ſeen under the Sun, namely, <hi>Riches</hi> kept for the owners thereof to their hurt. But thoſe <hi>Riches</hi> periſh by evil travel; and he begetteth a Son, and there is nothing in his hand, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.13, 14.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. A man to whom God had given <hi>Riches,</hi> Wealth and Honour, ſo that he wanteth nothing for his ſoul of all that he deſireth; yet God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth him not power to eat thereof, but a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger eateth it: this is vanity, and it is an evil di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, <hi>Ec.</hi> 6.2.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. By knowledge ſhall the chambers be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with all precious and pleaſant <hi>Riches,</hi> 24.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Righteous.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Righteous</hi> is more excellent than his neighbour; but the way of the wicked ſeduceth them, 12.26.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The mouth of a <hi>Righteous</hi> man is a Well of Life; but violence covereth the mouth of the wicked, 10.11.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:62"/>3. The lips of the <hi>Righteous</hi> feed many, but fools dye for want of wiſdom, 10.21.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The ſlothful covet all the day long, but the <hi>Righteous</hi> giveth and ſpareth not, 21.26.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. When the <hi>righteous</hi> are in authority, the people rejoyce; but when the wicked beareth rule, the people mourn, 29.2.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. In the tranſgreſſion of an evil man there is a ſnare; but the <hi>righteous</hi> doth ſing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, 29.6.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. When <hi>righteous</hi> men rejoyce, there is great glory; but when the wicked riſe, a man is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, 28.12.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. When it goeth well with the <hi>righteous,</hi> the City rejoyceth; and when the wicked pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, there is ſhouting, 11.10.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. A <hi>righteous</hi> man regardeth the life of his Beaſt; but the tender mercies of the wicked are cruel, 12.13.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. He that ſpeaketh truth, ſheweth forth <hi>righteouſneſs;</hi> but a falſe witneſs deceit, 12.17.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. A <hi>righteous</hi> man wiſely conſidereth the Houſe of the wicked; but God overthroweth the wicked for their wickedneſs, 21.12.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. The wicked flee when no man purſueth: but the <hi>righteous</hi> are bold as a Lyon, 28.1.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. The way of a ſlothful man is as a hedge of Thorns; but the way of the <hi>righteous</hi> is made plain, 15.19.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:63"/>14. The fruit of the <hi>Righteous</hi> is a tree of life, and he that winneth Souls is wiſe, 11.30.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. The labour of the <hi>Righteous</hi> tendeth to Life; the fruit of the wicked to ſin, 10.16.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. The wicked deſireth the net of evil men: but the root of the <hi>righteous</hi> yieldeth fruit, 12.12.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. The fear of the wicked it ſhall come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, but the deſire of the <hi>righteous</hi> ſhall be granted, 10.24.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. The Lord is far from the wicked; but he heareth the prayer of the <hi>righteous,</hi> 15.29.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. The <hi>Righteous</hi> is delivered out of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the wicked cometh in his ſtead, 11.8.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. The wicked ſhall be a ranſom for the <hi>Righteous:</hi> and the tranſgreſſor for the upright, 21.18.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. Behold the <hi>Righteous</hi> ſhall be recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the earth; much more the wicked and the ſinner, 11.31.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. When the wicked are multiplied, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion increaſeth; but the <hi>righteous</hi> ſhall ſee their fall, 29.16.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. Evil purſueth ſinners; but to the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi> good ſhall be repayed, 13.21.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. The <hi>righteous</hi> man eateth to the ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Soul; but the belly of the wicked ſhall want, 13.25.</p>
                  <p n="25">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:64"/>25. The Lord will not ſuffer the <hi>righteous</hi> to famiſh; but he caſteth away the ſubſtance of the wicked, 10.3.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. As the whirlwind paſſeth, ſo is the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no more; but the <hi>righteous</hi> is an everlaſting foundation, 10.25.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. The <hi>righteous</hi> ſhall never be removed; but the wicked ſhall not inhabit the earth. 10.30.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. A man ſhall not be eſtabliſh'd by wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; but the rod of the <hi>righteous</hi> ſhall not be moved, 12.3.</p>
                  <p n="29">29. The light of the <hi>righteous</hi> rejoyceth; but the lamp of the wicked ſhall be put out, 13.9.</p>
                  <p n="30">30. The way of the wicked is an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Lord; but he loveth him that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth after <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> 15.9.</p>
                  <p n="31">31. Better is a little with <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> than great Revenues without right, 16.8.</p>
                  <p n="32">32. <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> exalteth a Nation; but ſin is a reproach to any people, 14.34.</p>
                  <p n="33">33. Treaſures of wickedneſs profit nothing; but <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> delivereth from death, 10.2.</p>
                  <p n="34">34. The wicked worketh a deceitful work; but to him that ſoweth <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> ſhall be a ſure reward, 11.18.</p>
                  <p n="35">35. The <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> of the perfect ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his way; but the wicked will fall by his own wickedneſs, 11.5.</p>
                  <p n="36">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:65"/>36. In the way of <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> is life, and in the path-way thereof is no death, 12.28.</p>
                  <p n="37">37. <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> keepeth him that is upright in the way; but wickedneſs overthroweth the ſinner, 13.6.</p>
                  <p n="38">38. As <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> tendeth to life; ſo he that purſueth evil, purſueth it to his own death, 11.19.</p>
                  <p n="39">39. Lay not wait (O wicked man) againſt the dwelling place of the <hi>Righteous;</hi> ſpoil not his reſting place, 24.15.</p>
                  <p n="40">40. A <hi>Righteous</hi> man falling down before the wicked, is as a troubled Fountain, and a corrupt Spring, 25.26.</p>
                  <p n="41">41. He that ſaith to the wicked, Thou art <hi>righteous;</hi> him ſhall the people curſe, Nations ſhall abhor him, 24.24.</p>
                  <p n="42">42. Be not <hi>Righteous</hi> overmuch, neither make thy ſelf over-wiſe; why ſhouldeſt thou deſtroy thy ſelf, <hi>Eccl?</hi> 7.16.</p>
                  <p n="43">43. All things are alike to all; there is one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent to the <hi>righteous,</hi> and to the wicked; to the good, and to the clean, and to the unclean, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Rule.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He that <hi>ruleth</hi> over his own ſpirit, is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than he that taketh a City, 16.32.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that hath no <hi>rule</hi> over his own ſpirit, is like a City that is broken, and without Walls, 25.28.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:66"/>3. There is a time when one man <hi>ruleth</hi> over another to his own hurt. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.9.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. As a roaring Lion, and a ranging Bear; ſo is a wicked <hi>Ruler</hi> over the poor people, 28.15.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. If a <hi>Ruler</hi> hearken to lies, all his ſervants are wicked, 29.12..</p>
                  <p n="6">6. If the ſpirit of the <hi>Ruler</hi> riſe up againſt thee, leave not thy place; for yielding pacifieth great offences, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.4.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Be not deſirous of the dainties of the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler;</hi> for they are deceitful meats, 23.3.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="s" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Sacrifice.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of the wicked is an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Lord; but the prayer of the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right is his delight, 15.8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of the wicked is an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; how much more when he bringeth it with a wicked mind?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To do juſtice and judgment, is more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the Lord than <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> 21.3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Safety.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The Horſe is prepared againſt Battel; but <hi>Safety</hi> is of the Lord 21.31.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Scorn</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A <hi>Scorner</hi> ſeeketh wiſdom and findeth it not; but knowledge is eaſie to him that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth, 14.6.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:67"/>2. A <hi>Scorner</hi> loveth not him that reproveth him, neither will he go unto the wiſe, 15.12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Caſt out the <hi>Scorner,</hi> and contention ſhall go out; yea ſtrife and reproach ſhall ceaſe, 22.10.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A <hi>Scornful</hi> man bringeth a City into a ſnare; but wiſe men turn away wrath, 29.8.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Smite a <hi>Scorner</hi> and the ſimple will beware, 19.25.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. When the <hi>Scorner</hi> is puniſhed, the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is made wiſe; and when the wiſe is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed he receiveth knowledge, 21.11.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The Lord <hi>Scorneth</hi> the <hi>Scorner,</hi> but giveth grace to the lowly, 3.34.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The <hi>Scorner</hi> is an abomination to men, 24.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Seaſon.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. To every thing there is a <hi>Seaſon;</hi> and to every purpoſe there is a time and judgment, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Seed.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. In the morning ſow thy <hi>Seed,</hi> and in the evening withhold not thy hand; for thou knoweſt not, <hi>&amp;c. Eccl.</hi> 11.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Silver.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He that loveth <hi>Silver</hi> ſhall not be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Silver;</hi> and he that loveth abundance, with increaſe, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:68"/>
                  <head>Servant.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Accuſe not a <hi>Servant</hi> unto his Maſter, leſt he curſe thee, and thou be found guilty, 30.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A wiſe <hi>Servant</hi> ſhall have rule over a Son that cauſeth ſhame, and ſhall have part of the inheritance among the Brethren, 17.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Kings favour is towards a wiſe <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant;</hi> but his wrath is againſt him that cauſeth ame, 14.25.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He that delicately bringeth up his <hi>Servant</hi> from a Child, ſhall have him become his Son at the length, 29.21.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. When a <hi>Servant</hi> reigneth, the Earth is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted, 30.21, 22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Slothful.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A <hi>Slothful</hi> man ſaith, there is a Lion in the ſtreet, I ſhall be ſlain in the ſtreet, 26.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A <hi>Slothful</hi> man hideth his hand in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and it grieveth him to bring it unto his mouth again, 26.15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>Sluggard</hi> is wiſer in his own conceit, than ſeven men that can render a reaſon, 26.16.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. As a door turneth up the hinges, ſo doth a <hi>Slothful</hi> man upon his Bed, 26.14.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The deſire of the <hi>Slothful</hi> killeth him, for his hands refuſeth labour, 21.25.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The way of the <hi>Slothful</hi> man is a hedge of Thorns, 15.19.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:69"/>7. He that is <hi>ſlothful</hi> in his work, is brother to him that is a great waſter, 18.9.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. I went by the field of the <hi>ſlothful,</hi> and by the Vineyard of the man void of underſtanding: and lo it was all grown over with Thorns, and Nettles had covered the face thereof, and the ſtone-wall thereof was broken down, 24, 30.31.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 By much <hi>Slothfulneſs</hi> the Building decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and through idlenſs of the hands the houſe droppeth through, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.18.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. <hi>Slothfulneſs</hi> caſteth into a deep ſleep, and an idle Soul ſhall ſuffer hunger, 19.15.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. The <hi>Sluggard</hi> will not plough by reaſon of cold; therefore ſhall he beg in Harveſt, and have nothing, 20.4.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. As Vinegar to the Teeth, and as Smoak to the Eyes; ſo is a <hi>Sluggard</hi> to them that ſend him, 10.26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Spirit.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Spirit</hi> of a man is the Candle of the Lord, ſearching all the inward parts of the belly, 20.27.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Who knoweth the <hi>Spirit</hi> of a man that goeth upward, and the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Beaſt that goeth downward to the Earth? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.21.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As thou knoweſt not what is the way of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> nor how the bones grow in the womb of her that is with child; even ſo thou knoweſt not the work of God that maketh all, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.5.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:70"/>4. There is no man that hath power of the <hi>Spirit</hi> to retain the <hi>Spirit;</hi> neither hath he pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the day of death; and there is no diſcharge in that war; neither ſhall wickedneſs deliver them that are given to it, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.8.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The <hi>Spirit</hi> of man will bear his infirmity; but a wounded <hi>Spirit</hi> who can bear? 18.14.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. By ſorrow of heart the <hi>Spirit</hi> is broken, 15.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Stones.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Whoſo removeth <hi>Stones</hi> ſhall be hurt therewith; and he that cleaveth wood, ſhall be endangered thereby, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Study.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Of making Books there is no end; and much <hi>ſtudy</hi> is a wearineſs to the fleſh, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Sun.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. There is no new thing under the <hi>Sun, Eccl.</hi> 1.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Strife.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The beginning of <hi>ſtrife</hi> is as when one letteth out waters; therefore leave off conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before it be medled with, 17.14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The churning of milk bringeth forth But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the wringing of the Noſe bringeth forth blood; ſo the forcing of wrath bringeth forth <hi>ſtrife,</hi> 30.33.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:71"/>3. He loveth tranſgreſſion that loveth <hi>ſtrife;</hi> and he that exalteth his gate, ſeeketh deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, 17.19.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Where no wood is, the fire goeth out; ſo where there is no tale-bearer, the <hi>ſtrife</hi> ceaſeth, 26.20.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. A wrathful man ſtirreth up <hi>ſtrife;</hi> but he that is ſlow to anger, appeaſeth <hi>ſtrife,</hi> 15.18.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. He that paſſeth by and medleth with <hi>ſtrife</hi> that belongeth not to him, is like one that taketh a dog by the ears, 26.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Surety.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Be not thou one of them that ſtrike hands, nor of them that are <hi>Sureties</hi> for debts: If thou haſt nothing to pay, why ſhould he take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy bed from under thee? 22.26, 27.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A man void of underſtanding ſtriketh hands, and becometh <hi>Surety</hi> in the preſence of his friend, 17.18.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Take his Garment that is <hi>Surety</hi> for a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and take a pledge of him for a ſtrange Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, 23.16.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. My Son, if thou be <hi>Surety</hi> for thy friend, if thou haſt ſtricken thy hand with a ſtranger, thou art ſnared with the words of thy mouth, thou art taken with the words of thy wouth, 6.1.2.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He that is <hi>Surety</hi> for a ſtranger, ſhall ſmart for it; and he that hateth <hi>Suretyſhip,</hi> is ſure, 11.15.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="t" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:72"/>
                  <head>Tale-bearer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A <hi>Tale-bearer</hi> revealeth ſecrets; but he that is of a faithful ſpirit concealeth the matter, 11.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The words of a <hi>Tale-bearer</hi> are as wounds, and they go down into the innermoſt parts of the belly, 18.8.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He that goeth about as a <hi>Tale-bearer,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealeth ſecrets; therefore meddle not with him that flattereth with his Lips, 20.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Thief</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Whoſo is partner with a <hi>Thief,</hi> hateth his own ſoul; he heareth curſing, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayeth it not, 29.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Thoughts.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>thoughts</hi> of fooliſhneſs is ſin, 24.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>thoughts</hi> of the wicked are an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Lord; but the words of the pure are pleaſant words. 15.26.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Commit thy works unto the Lord, and thy <hi>Thoughts</hi> ſhall be eſtabliſhed, 16.3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Tongue.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Death and Life are in the power of the <hi>Tongue;</hi> they that love it, ſhall eat the fruit thereof, 18.21.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whoſo keepeth his mouth and <hi>tongue,</hi> keepeth his Soul from trouble, 21.23.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:73"/>3. A wholſom <hi>Tongue</hi> is a tree of life; but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſs therein is a breach of the ſpirit, 15.4.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A ſoft <hi>Tongue</hi> breaketh the bone, 25.15.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. A virtuous woman openeth her mouth with wiſdom, and in her <hi>Tongue</hi> is the law of kindneſs, 31.26.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. There is that ſpeaketh like the piercings of a ſword; but the <hi>Tongue</hi> of the wiſe is health, 12.18.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The North-wind driveth away rain; ſo doth an angry countenance a backbiting <hi>Tongue,</hi> 25.23.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. He that hath a perverſe <hi>Tongue</hi> falleth into miſchief, 17.20.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. The <hi>Tongue</hi> of the juſt is as choice ſilver, 10.20.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. The <hi>Tongue</hi> of the wiſe uſeth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge aright; but the mouth of fools poureth out fooliſhneſs, 15.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Tree.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. If the <hi>Tree</hi> fall towards the <hi>South,</hi> or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the North; in the place where the <hi>Tree</hi> falleth there it ſhall be, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Truth.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. My mouth ſhall ſpeak <hi>Truth;</hi> and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is an abomination to my Lips, 8.7.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The lips of <hi>Truth</hi> ſhall be eſtabliſhed for ever, 12.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:74"/>3. Buy the <hi>Truth</hi> and ſell it not: alſo wiſdom, and inſtruction, and underſtanding, 23.23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Truſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Truſt</hi> in the Lord with all thy heart, and lean not to thine own underſtanding, 3.5.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="v" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Vanity.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He that ſoweth iniquity, ſhall reap <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and the rod of his anger ſhall fail, 22.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Violence.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Evil men eat the bread of wickedneſs, and drink the wine of <hi>Violence,</hi> 4.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A man that doth <hi>Violence</hi> to the blood of any perſon, ſhall flee to the pit, let no man ſtay him, 28.17.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The ſoul of the tranſgreſſor ſhall eat <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> 13.2.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A <hi>Violent</hi> man enticeth his neighbour, and leadeth him into the way that is not good, 16.29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Vnderſtanding.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Happy is the man that findeth wiſdom, and the man that getteth <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> 3.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Wiſdom is the principal thing, therefore get wiſdom; and with all thy gettings, get <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> 4.7.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How much is it better to get wiſdom, than Gold? and to get <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> rather to be choſen than ſilver? 16.16.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:75"/>4. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> is a Well of Life to them that have it, but the inſtruction of fools is fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, 16 22.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Good <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> giveth favour; but the way of the tranſgreſſor is hard, 13.15.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Diſcretion ſhall preſerve thee, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> ſhall keep thee, 2.11.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. He that getteth wiſdom, loveth his own ſoul: he that keepeth <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> ſhall find good, 19.8.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The man that wandreth out of the way of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> ſhall remain in the congregation of the dead, 21.16.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Say unto Wiſdom, thou art my Siſter, and call <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> thy kinſwoman, 7.4.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. There is no wiſdom, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> nor counſel againſt the Lord, 21.30.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Vngodly.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. An <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly</hi> man diggeth up evil, and in his lips there is a burning fire, 16.27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Vnjuſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. He that by Uſury and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt</hi> gain increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his ſubſtance, he ſhall gather it for him that ſhall pity the poor, 28.8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. An <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt</hi> man is an abomination to the juſt, and he that is upright in his way, is an abomination to the wicked, 29.27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:76"/>
                  <head>Vpright.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. God hath made man <hi>upright,</hi> but they have ſought out many inventions, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.29.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They that are of a froward heart, are an abomination to the Lord; but ſuch as are <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right</hi> in their way, are his delight, 11.20.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The highway of the <hi>upright</hi> is to depart from evil; but he that keepeth his way preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth his Soul, 16.17.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He that walketh in his <hi>uprightneſs</hi> feareth the Lord; but he that is perverſe in his way deſpiſeth him, 14.2.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He that walketh <hi>uprightly,</hi> walketh ſurely; but he that perverteth his way, ſhall be known, 10.9.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The way of the Lord is ſtrength to the <hi>upright;</hi> but deſtruction ſhall be to the workers of iniquity, 10.29.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The Lord lays up ſound wiſdom for the righteous, he is a buckler to them that walk <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly,</hi> 2.7.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A wicked man hardeneth his Face; but as for the <hi>upright</hi> he directeth his way, 21.29.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Whoſo walketh <hi>uprightly</hi> ſhall be ſaved; but he that is perverſe in his ways, ſhall fall at once, 28.18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:77"/>
                  <head>Vow.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. It is a ſnare to the man who devoureth that which is holy, and after <hi>Vows</hi> to make en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, 20.25.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="w" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Water.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Stolen <hi>Waters</hi> are ſweet, and bread eaten in ſecret is pleaſant, 9.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>War.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. There is a <hi>way</hi> that ſeemeth right to a man, but the end thereof are the ways of death, 14.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>way</hi> of the wickd is darkneſs, they know not at what they ſtumble, 4.19.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>way</hi> of life, is above to the wiſe, that they may depart from Hell beneath, 15.24.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Hear thou my Son, and be wiſe, and guide thy heart in the <hi>way,</hi> 23.19.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 Walk in the <hi>way</hi> of good men, and keep the paths of the righteous, 2.20.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Mans goings are of the Lord, how can a man then underſtand his own <hi>way?</hi> 20.24.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. In all thy <hi>ways</hi> acknowledge him, and he ſhall direct thy paths, 3.6.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Ponder the path of thy feet, and let all thy wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s be eſtabliſhed, 4.26.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. The Lord keepeth the paths of judgment, and preſerveth the <hi>way</hi> of the Saints, 2.8.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:78"/>10. There be three things which are too wonderful for me, yea, four which I know not; The <hi>way</hi> of an Eagle in the air; the <hi>way</hi> of a Serpent upon a Rock; the <hi>way</hi> of a Ship in the midſt of the Sea; and the <hi>way</hi> of a Man with a Maid, 30.18, 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wander.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. As a Bird that <hi>wandereth</hi> from her Neſt, ſo is a Man that <hi>wandereth</hi> from his place, 27.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wealth.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Wealth</hi> gotten by vanity, ſhall be dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; but he that gathereth by labour, ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, 13.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Every man to whom God hath given riches, and <hi>wealth,</hi> and hath given him power to eat thereof, and to take his portion, and to rejoyce in his labour; this is the gift of God, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Water.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Drink <hi>water</hi> out of thine own Ciſtern, and running <hi>waters</hi> out of thine own Well, 5.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let thy fountains be diſperſed abroad, and rivers of <hi>waters</hi> in the ſtreets; let them only be thy own, and not ſtrangers with thee. 5.16, 17.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The words of a mans mouth are as deep <hi>waters,</hi> and the well-ſprings of Wiſdom like a flowing Brook, 18.4.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:79"/>4. Caſt thy bread upon the <hi>Waters,</hi> for thou ſhalt find it after many days, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Weight.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Divers <hi>weights,</hi> and divers meaſures, both of them are like abomination to the Lord, 20.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Divers <hi>weights</hi> are an abomination to the Lord, and a falſe ballance is not good, 20.23.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A juſt <hi>weight</hi> and ballance are the Lords, and all the <hi>weights</hi> of the bag are his work, 16.11.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A falſe ballance is an abomination to the Lord; but a juſt <hi>weight</hi> is his delight, 11.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wicked.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Be not over-much wicked, neither be thou fooliſh; why ſhouldeſt thou dye before thy time? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Enter not into the path of the <hi>wicked,</hi> and go not in the way of evil men, 4.14.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. When the <hi>wicked</hi> cometh, then cometh al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo contempt, and with ignominy reproach, 18.3.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. There ſhall no evil happen to the juſt, but the <hi>wicked</hi> ſhall be filled with miſchief, 12.21.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The ſoul of the <hi>wicked</hi> deſireth evil, his neighbour findeth no favour in his eyes, 21.10.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. His own iniquities ſhall take the <hi>wicked</hi> himſelf, and he ſhall be holden with the cords <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his ſins, 5.22.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Fret not thy ſelf becauſe of evil men, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be thou envious at the <hi>wicked,</hi> 24.19.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:80"/>8. I ſaw the <hi>wicked</hi> buried, who had come and gone from the place of the holy, and they were forgotten in the City when they had ſo done: this is alſo vanity, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.10.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. The Lord hath made all things for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, even the <hi>wicked</hi> for the day of evil, 16.4.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. There ſhall be no reward to the evil man; the candle of the <hi>wicked</hi> ſhall be put out, 24.20.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. A good man obtaineth favour of the Lord; but a man of <hi>wicked</hi> devices ſhall he condemn, 12.2.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Be not afraid of ſudden fear, nor of the deſolation of the <hi>wicked</hi> when it cometh, 3.25.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. The <hi>wicked</hi> ſhall be cut off from the earth, and the tranſgreſſor ſhal be rooted out of it, 2 22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wife.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Houſe and riches are the inheritance of fathers, but a prudent <hi>wife</hi> is from the Lord. 19.14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whoſo findeth a <hi>wife</hi> findeth a good thing, and obtaineth favour of the Lord, 18.22.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Let thy fountain be bleſſed, rejoyce in the <hi>wife</hi> of thy youth, 5.18.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Live joyfully with thy <hi>wife</hi> whom thou loveſt, all the days of the life of thy vanity, which God hath given thee under the Sun; for that is thy portion in this life, and in thy labour which thou takeſt under the Sun, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.9.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:81"/>5. A fooliſh Son is the calamity of his Father; and the contentions of a <hi>Wife</hi> are a continual dropping, 19.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wind.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. What profit hath he that hath laboured for the <hi>wind? Eccl.</hi> 5.16.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that obſerveth the <hi>wind</hi> ſhall not ſow; and he that regardeth the clouds, ſhall not reap, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wine.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Wine</hi> is a mocker, ſtrong drink is raging: and whoſever is deceived thereby is not wiſe, 20.1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Who hath woe? who hath ſorrow? who hath contentions? who hath babling? who hath wounds? who hath redneſs of, eyes? They that tarry long at the <hi>wine,</hi> they that go to ſeek mixt <hi>wine,</hi> 23.29, 30.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Look not thou upon the <hi>wine</hi> when it is Red, when it giveth its colour in the cup, when it moveth it ſelf aright. At laſt it biteth like a Serpent; and ſtingeth like an Adder. Thine eyes ſhall behold ſtrange women, and thy heart ſhall utter perverſe things, 23.31, 32, 33.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Give ſtrong drink unto him that is ready to periſh, and <hi>Wine</hi> unto thoſe that be of heavy hearts. Let him drink, and forget his poverty, and remember his miſery no more, 31.6, 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:82"/>
                  <head>Wiſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Bow down thine ears, and hear the words of the <hi>wiſe,</hi> and apply thy heart to wiſdom, 22.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. My ſon, if thy heart be <hi>wiſe,</hi> my heart ſhall rejoyce, even mine, 23.15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A <hi>wiſe</hi> man will hear, and increaſe learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and a man of underſtanding ſhall attain to wiſe counſels, 1.5.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In the multitude of words there wanteth not ſin; but he that refraineth his lips is <hi>wiſe,</hi> 10.19.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The heart of the <hi>wiſe</hi> teacheth his mouth, and addeth learning to his lips, 16.23.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. There is treaſure to be deſired, and oyl in the dwelling-place of the <hi>wiſe;</hi> but a fooliſh man ſpendeth it up, 21.20.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Theſe things alſo belong to the <hi>wiſe;</hi> It is not good to have reſpect of perſons in judgment, 24.23.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The words of the <hi>wiſe</hi> are as goads, and as nails faſtned by the maſters of Aſſemblies, which are given from one ſhepherd, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.11.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. There be four things that be little upon the earth, but they are exceeding <hi>wiſe,</hi> the Ants, the Conies, the Locuſts, and the Spiders, 30.24.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Go to the Ant thou ſluggard, conſider her ways and be <hi>wiſe,</hi> 6.6.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:83"/>11. If a <hi>wiſe</hi> man contendeth with a fooliſh man, whether he rage or laugh there is no reſt, 29.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wiſdom.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. I <hi>wiſdom</hi> dwell with prudence, and find out knowledge of witty inventions, 8.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is better than rubies; and all things that may be deſired, are not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to it, 8.11.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is better than weapons of war; but one ſinner deſtroyeth much good, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.18.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is better than ſtrength; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs the poor mans <hi>wiſdom</hi> is deſpiſed, and his words are not heard, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9 16.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Wiſdom</hi> ſtrengtheneth the wiſe, more than ten mighty men who are in the City, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.19.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is too high for a fool, he openeth not his mouth in the gate, 24.7.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. He that handleth a matter <hi>wiſely,</hi> ſhall find good; and whoſo truſteth in the Lord, happy is he, 16.20.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Through deſire a man having ſeparated himſelf, ſeeketh and intermedleth with all <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> 18.18.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Say not thou, What is the cauſe that the former days were better than theſe? for thou doſt not enquire <hi>wiſely</hi> concerning this, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.10.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:84"/>10. In much <hi>wiſdom</hi> is much grief; and he that encreaſeth knowledg, encreaſeth ſorrow, <hi>Ec</hi> 1.18</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Witneſs</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The Lord hates a falſe <hi>witneſs,</hi> that ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth lies; 6.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A faithful <hi>witneſs</hi> will not lye; but a falſe <hi>witneſs</hi> will utter lies, 14.5.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A falſe <hi>witneſs</hi> ſhall not be unpuniſhed; and he that ſpeaketh lies ſhall not eſcape, 19.5.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A falſe <hi>witneſs</hi> ſhall periſh; but a man that heareth, ſpeaketh conſtantly, 21.28.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 A man that heareth falſe <hi>witneſs</hi> againſt his Neighbour, is a Maul, and a Sword, and a ſharp Arrow, 25.18.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. A true <hi>witneſs</hi> delivereth ſouls; but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful one ſpeaketh lies, 14 25.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. An ungodly <hi>witneſs</hi> ſcorneth judgment; and the mouth of the wicked devoureth ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, 19.28.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Be not <hi>witneſs</hi> againſt thy neighbour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe; and deceive not with thy lips, 24 28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Woman.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A fooliſh <hi>woman</hi> is clamorous and ſimple, and knoweth nothing, 9 13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The lips of a ſtrange <hi>woman</hi> drop as an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney comb; her mouth is ſmoother than oil, but her end is bitter as wormwood, ſharp as a two-edged-ſword; her feet go down to death, her ſteps take hold of hell, 5.3, 4, 5.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:85"/>3. Wiſdom will deliver thee from a ſtrange <hi>woman,</hi> the ſtranger that flattereth with her words, which forſaketh the guide of her youth, and forgetteth the covenant of her God: for her houſe inclineth unto death, and her paths unto the dead, 2.16, 17, 18.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Remove thy way far from the ſtrange <hi>Woman,</hi> and come not near the door of her houſe; leſt thou give thine honor unto others, and thy years to the cruel; leſt ſtrangers be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with thy wealth, and thy labours be in the houſe of a ſtranger; and thou mourn at the laſt when thy fleſh and body are conſumed; and ſay, how have I hated inſtruction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 5.9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. For three things the earth is diſquieted, and for four it cannot bear; for a Servant when he reigneth, and a fool when he is filled with meat; for an odious <hi>Woman</hi> when ſhe is Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and an hand-maid that is Heir to her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſs, 30.21, 22, 23.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. I find more bitter than death, the <hi>Woman</hi> whoſe heat is ſnares and nets, and her hands as bands; whoſo pleaſeth God ſhall eſcape from her; but the ſinner ſhall be taken by her, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.26.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The mouth of a ſtrange <hi>Woman</hi> is a deep pit; he that is abhorred of the Lord, ſhall fall therein, 22.14.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Give not thy ſtrength to <hi>Women,</hi> nor thy ways to that which deſtroyeth Kings, 31.3.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:86"/>9. Why wilt thou my Son be raviſht with a ſtrange <hi>Woman,</hi> and embrace the boſom of a ſtranger? for the ways of a man are before the eyes of the Lord, and he pondereth all his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, 5.20, 21.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Keep the Commandment, and it will keep thee from the evil <hi>Woman,</hi> from the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of the tongue of a ſtrange <hi>Woman:</hi> luſt not after her Beauty in thine heart, neither let her take thee with her eye-lids, 6.24.25.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. As a jewel of Gold in a Swines ſnout; ſo is a fair <hi>woman</hi> without diſcretion, 11.22.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. A virtuous <hi>Woman</hi> is a Crown to her Husband; but ſhe that maketh aſhamed, is as rottenneſs to his bones, 12.4.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Every wiſe <hi>Woman</hi> buildeth her Houſe, but a fooliſh <hi>Woman</hi> pulleth it down with he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hands, 14.1.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. It is better to dwell in the corner of a Houſe-top, than with a brawling <hi>Woman</hi> in a wide houſe, 25.24.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. It is better to dwell in the Wilderneſs, than with a contentious and angry <hi>Woman,</hi> 21.19.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Who can find a virtuous <hi>Woman?</hi> for her price is above Rubies, 31.10.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. One Man among a thouſand have I found; but a <hi>Woman</hi> among all theſe have I not found, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.28.</p>
                  <p n="18">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:87"/>18. Favour is deceitful, and Beauty is vain; but a <hi>Woman</hi> that feareth the Lord, ſhe ſhall be praiſed. Give her of the fruit of her hands, and let her own works praiſe her in the Gate, 31.30, 31.</p>
                  <p n="29">29. Whoſo hideth the contentious <hi>Woman,</hi> hideth the Wind; and the ointment of his right Hand which bewrayeth it ſelf, 27.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Word.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Heavineſs in the heart of man maketh it ſtoop; but a good <hi>word</hi> maketh it glad, 12.25.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Pleaſant <hi>words</hi> are as the Hony-comb, ſweet to the Soul, and health to the Bones, 16.24.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A <hi>word</hi> fitly ſpoken, is like apples of Gold in pictures of Silver, 25.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wrath.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A man of great <hi>wrath</hi> ſhall ſuffer puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for if thou deliver him, yet thou muſt do it again, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.19.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171177:11"/>
            <head>PROVERBIA <hi>Solomonis,</hi> Alphabetice Collecta Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriae gratiâ.</head>
            <div n="a" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Adverſity.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 SI tu deficio in tempus anguſtia, tuus virtus ſum anguſtus, <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Amicus diligo omnis tempus, &amp; frater naſcor in anguſtiâ, 17.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In tempus bonum laetor; autem in tempus malum conſidero, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Adultery.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Quiſquis perpetro Adulterium cum Muli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, careo intelligentia, qui facio iſte, perdo ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſuus, 6.32.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Is ſum via ſcortans Mulier: comedo, &amp; abſtergo ſuus os &amp; dico, operor nullus iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, 30.20.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:12"/>3. Nam propter ſcortans mulier homo dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co ad fruſtrum panis; &amp; adultera venor pretioſus vita, 6.26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Affliction.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Omnis dies afflictus ſum malus, ſed qui ſum laetus animus, habeo continuus convivium, 15.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Anger.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Intellectus homo defero ſuus ira, &amp; ſum ornamentum is praetereo defectio, 19.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui ſum tardus ad ira, ſum melior robu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, 16.32.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Exerceo nullus amicitia cum iracundus, &amp; cum furibundus non congredior, ne diſco iter is, 22.24.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Iracundus excito contentio, &amp; furibun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus abundo defectio, 29.22.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Qui ſum cito iratus, facio ſtulte: Et homo cogitatio fraudulentus ſum odium, 14, 17.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Ne perturbor in ſpiritus ut indignor, nam indignatio conquieſco in ſinus ſtultus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Homo habeo laetitia ex ſermo os, &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum prolatus debitus tempus quam bonus ſum 15.23.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:13"/>2. Animus juſtus meditor ad reſpondeo; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem os improbus eructo malus, 15.28.</p>
                  <p n="3">3, Unuſquiſque oſculor labium is, qui reddo rectus reſponſum, 24.26.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Mollis reſponſio averto excandeſcentia: au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem verbum moleſtus excito ira, 15.1.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Ne reſpondeo ſtolidus ſecundum ſtultitia is, ne tu ſum ſimilis ille, 26 4.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Reſpondeo ſtolidus ſecundum ſtultitia is, ne ſum ſapiens in oculus ſuus, 26.5.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Qui reſpondeo aliquis priuſquam audio, ſum ſtultitia &amp; ignominia is, 18.13.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Preparatio cor, &amp; reſponſio lingua, ſum a Dominus, 16.1.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="b" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Babler.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Serpens mordeo ſine incantatio, nec gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulus ſum melior, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Backſlider.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Tergiverſator in animus ſatio ſuus via, &amp; vir bonus ſatio a ſui ipſius. 14.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Bleſſing.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Benedictio Jehova dito, neque addo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtia cum ſui, 10.22.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:14"/>2. Bene dictio adſum caput juſtus, at vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia obtego os impius, 10.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Blood thirſty.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Homo ſanguinarius odi integer: autem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus quaero anima is, 22.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Brother.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Frater provocatus ſum difficilior vinco urbs munitus, &amp; contentio hic ſum ut vectis arx, 18.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Ne ingredier domus frater tempus calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas: Melior ſum vicinus propinquus frater lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginquus, 27.10.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="c" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Cauſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui ſum primus in lis ſuus videor juſtus; autem proximus is advenio &amp; perveſtigo is, 18.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Ago cauſa tuus cum proximus tuus ipſe: ſed ne retego arcanum alter, 25.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Aperio os tuus pro mutus in cauſa omnis qui trado excidium, 31.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Chaſten.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Ne ſperno eruditio Jehovah neque taedet tu correctio is, 3.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Caſtigo filius tuus dum ſum ſpes, nec ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus tuus condono propter clamor ipſe, 19.18.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:15"/>3, Qui cohibeo virga ſuus odi filius ſuus; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem qui amo is caſtigo ille tempeſtive, 13.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Child.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Unuſquiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> puer cognoſco actio ſuus an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus is ſum purus, &amp; an ſum rectus, 20.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Stultitia alligo animus puer; autem virga eruditio amoveo is procul ab ipſe, 22.15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Ne ſubtraho correctio a puer tuus, enim ſi percutio is virga, non morior, 23.13.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. At puer permiſſus ſui pudefacio mater ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, 29.15.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Pater Juſtus valde exulto, &amp; qui gigno ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piens puer laetor de is, 23.24.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Melior ſum indigus ſapiens puer, ſenex ſtolidus Rex, qui volo non amplius admoneo, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.13.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Sum qui habeo nec filius nec frater, nec ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſum finis labor, nec oculus is ſatio divitiae, nec dico, Qui ego laboro &amp; deſtituo anima me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us bonum, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4 8.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Filius filius ſum corona Senex, &amp; orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum filius ſum Pater ipſe, 17.6.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:16"/>9. Siquis gigno liberi centenus, &amp; vivo mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus annus, adeo ut dies annus is ſum multus, &amp; anima is non ſatio bonum, &amp; nec ſum ſepultura is, dico abortivus ſum melior ille, <hi>Ec.</hi> 6.3.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Inſtruo Puer in via, qui oportet eo; &amp; cum ſeneſco, non recedo ab is, 22.6.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Video omnis vivens qui ambulo ſub Sol cum ſecundus Puer, qui ſto locus is, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>City.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Labor ſtolidus fatigo quiſque ipſe, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam neſcio eo in civitas, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Cord.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Triplicatus filum non cito abrumpor, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Crooked.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui ſum perverſus, non poſſum corrigor; &amp; qui deficio non poſſum numeror, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:17"/>
                  <head>Confidence.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Fiducia in perfidus dies anguſtia, ſum ut fractus dens, &amp; pes luxatus, 25.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sapiens timeo &amp; recedo a malum; vero ſtolidus excandeſco, &amp; ſum ſecurus, 14.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Commandment.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Quiſquis contemno Verbum, corrumpo; autem qui revereor Praeceptum, rependo, 13. 13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui obſervo Praeceptum ſervo anima ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us; autem qui ſperno ſuus via morior, 19.16.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Sapiens animus accipio praeceptum, ſed loquax ſtultus cado, 10.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Comely.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sum tres qui procedo bene, imo quatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or ſum decorus in ambulo, Leo qui ſum robu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſſimus inter beſtia, nec retrogredior metus quiquam; Vertagus &amp; Caper etiam; &amp; Rex in qui ſum nullus inſurrectio, 30.29, 30.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Contentious.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Ut carbo ſum ad pruna &amp; lignum ad ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, ita ſum contentioſus vir ad accendo lis, 26.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:18"/>
                  <head>Corn.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui retineo triticum populus execro ille, autem benedictio incumbo caput vendens ille, 11.26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Correct.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Caſtigo tuus filius &amp; affero quies tu, imo do deliciae tuus anima, 29.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Correctio ſum gravis derelinquens Iter, &amp; qui odi correptio morior, 15.10.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Servus non caſtigo verbum, enim quamvis intelligo non reſpondeo, 29.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Counſel.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Ubi nullus concilium ſum populus corruo, autem in amplitudo conſiliarius ſum ſalus, 11.14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Auſculto conſilium, &amp; accipio eruditio ut ſapio in dies tuus ultimus, 19.20.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Sine conſilium cogitatio fio irritus, at in amplitudo conſiliarius ſtabilio, 15.22.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Unuſquiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> propoſitum confirmo conſilium, &amp; prudens conſilium gero bellum, 20.18.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Conſilium in animus vir ſum ſimilis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundus aqua, attamen vir intelligens haurio ille, 20.5.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Inſum multus cogitatio animus homo, ſed conſilium Jehova ipſe ſto, 19, 21.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:19"/>7. Unguentum &amp; ſuffitus laetifico cor; ita dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedo amicus ſuus cordatus conſilium; 27.9.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Cogitatio Juſtus ſum juſtus, at conſilium improbus ſum doloſus, 12.5.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Dolus ſum in cor fabricans malum, autem conſiliarius pax ſum laetitia, 12.20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Cover.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui tego defectio quaero dilectio, verò qui renovo res disjungo etiam amicus, 17.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui tego ſuus defectio non proſperor, verò qui fateor &amp; derelinquo invenio miſericordia: 28.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Curſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Execratio Jehova incumbo domus impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, at benedico habitaculum juſtus, 3.33.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Ut avicula erro, ut Hirundo volito, ita ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledictio immeritus non advenio, 26.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Qui do pauper non egeo, vero qui occulto oculus ſuus ſum is multus maledictio, 28.27.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="d" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Deceit.</head>
                  <p n="8">8. Cibus falſitas ſum ſuavis vir, ſed poſtea os is impleo ſcrupus, 20.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui odi, ſimulo ſuus labium, &amp; repono do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus in medium ſui, 26.26.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:20"/>3. Qui odium tego deceptio, malitia is revelo coram totus Congregatio, 26.26.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Fidelis ſum vulnus amicus, verò oſculum oſor ſum doloſus, 27 6.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Pauper &amp; doloſus homo occurro unà, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hova illumino oculus ambo, 29 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Deſire.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Deſiderium effectus ſum ſuavis anima, at ſum abominatio ſtolidus recedo à malum, 13.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Deſiderium homo ſum is benignitas: &amp; pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſum melior mendax, 19.22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Deſpiſed.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Vir laudo pro ratio ſuus intellectus; ſed qui ſum perverſus animus contemno, 12.8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui contemno &amp; habeo ſervus; ſum melior is qui extollo ſui, &amp; deficior cib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, 12.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Deſtruction.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Ante confractio animus humanus extollo, &amp; ante honor ſum abjectio, 18.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Superbia ante eo confractio, &amp; ſpiritus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latus ante lapſus, 16.18.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Sepulchrum &amp; perditio nunquam Satio; ita oculus homo nunquam ſatio, 27.20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:21"/>
                  <head>Diligent.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Manus ſedulus dominor, autem ignavus ſum tributarius, 12.24.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Fio pauper qui ago ignavus manus, autem manus ſedulus dito, 10.4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Ignavus aſſo non qui capio venor; autem ſubſtantia ſedulus ſum pretioſus, 12.27.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Anima piger deſidero &amp; habeo nihil, verò anima ſedulus efficio pinguis, 13.4.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Cogitatio ſedulus tendo tantum ad copia: autem omnis praeceps tantum ad egeſtas, 21.5.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Videone vir diligens in ſuus opus? conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto ante Rex, non conſiſto ante obſcurus. 22.29.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Qui ſtudioſe quaero bonum conquiro bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volentia; vero qui quaero malum evenio ipſe, 11, 27</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Dreams.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. In multitudo Somnium &amp; multus verbum, inſum etiam varius vanitas, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.7.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Somnium prodor multus occupatio, &amp; vox ſtolidus cognoſco multitudo verbum, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.3.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="e" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:23"/>
                  <head>Ear.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Animus prudens poſſideo ſcientia, &amp; auris ſapiens quaero ſcientia, 18.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Audiens auris &amp; videns oculus, Jehova fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio aeque uterque, 20.12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Qui averto ſuus auris ab audio Lex, etiam oratio is ſum abominatio, 28.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Eat.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Veſcor tu ne cibus is qui ſum malignus ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus; ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> deſidero cupediae ille, 23.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Emolumentum Terra ſum pro omnis, Rex ipſe ſervio de ager, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Enemy.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Laetor ne quum tuus inimicus cado, ne ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus tuus exulto quum corruo, 24.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Si tuus oſor eſurio, do ille Panis ut edo, &amp; ſi ſitio do is aqua ut bibo, 25.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Envy.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. In video tu ne violentus, &amp; eligo nullus via is, 3.31.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Ne animus tuus aemulor peccator; ſum in reverentia Jehova totus dies, 23.17.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:24"/>3. Sanus animus ſum vita caro; vero inviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſum putredo os, 14.30.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Excandeſcentia ſum crudelis, &amp; ira ſum inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, at quis poſſum conſiſto coram invidentia, 27.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Evil.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Malus incurvo ſui coram bonus, &amp; improbus ad porta juſtus, 14.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Malus homo animadverto non jus; autem quaerens Jehova animadverto omnis, 28 5.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Defectio vir malus inſum tendicula; autem Juſtus canto &amp; laetor, 29.6.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Nonne ille erro qui fabrico malum? verò benignitas &amp; fides ſum fabricans bonum, 14.22.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Quiſquis reddo malum pro bonum, malum non recedo a domus ille, 17.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Eye.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui nicto oculus do moleſtia, at loquax ſtultus cado, 10.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Qui habeo benignus oculus benedico; nam do de panis ſuus tedius, 22.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Oculus qui ſubſanno Pater, &amp; ſperno obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio Mater, Corvus Vallis effodio hic, 30.17.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Singulus res ſum plenus labor, quiſquam non poſſum eloquor: Oculus non ſatio video, nec auris audio, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.8.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:25"/>5. Lumen Oculus laetifico animus, ita auditio, bonus pingue facio os, 15.30.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Oculus Jehova ſum in omnis locus, ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans malus &amp; bonus, 15.3.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Oculus Jehova cuſtodio ſcientia; autem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verto verbum perfidioſus, 22.12.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Sapiens Oculus ſum in ſuus caput; autem ſtolidus ambulo in tenebrae, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.14.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Melior ſum inſpectio Oculus, quam curſus deſiderium, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 6.9.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Ne ſum ſapiens judicium tuus, reveror Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hova &amp; recedo a malum, 3.7.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Via Stultus ſum rectus in ſuus Oculus; at qui auſculto conſilium ſum ſapiens, 12.15.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Unuſquiſque via homo ſum rectus in ſuus Oculus; ſed Jehova perpendo animus, 21.2.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Sum generatio mundus in ſuus Oculus, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamen non ambulo a ſuus ſordes, 30.12.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Tuus Oculus intueor e regione, &amp; tuus palpebra ſpecto recta coram tu, 4.25.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="f" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Face</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Homo ſapientia illuſtro facies is, &amp; firmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas vultus ille muto, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Father.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Auſculto Pater tuus qui gigno tu, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temno Mater tuus quum ſeneſco, 23.22.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:26"/>2. Audio filius eruditio Pater, &amp; attendo ad cognoſco prudentia, 4.1.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Sapiens filius facio laetus Pater, vero ſtolidus Filius ſum maeſtitia Mater ſuus, 10.1.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Qui gigno ſtolidus, gigno ad maeror ſuus; nec Pater ſtultus laetor, 17.21.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Sapiens Filius auſculto ſuus Pater eruditio, dum ſtultus ſperno is; autem qui obſervo correp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, ſum prudens, 13.1.—15.5.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Stolidus Filius ſum Indignatio ſuus Pater; &amp; amaritudo ſuus genetrix, 17.25.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Qui devaſto Pater, &amp; fugo Mater, ſum Filius qui pudefacio &amp; infero probrum, 19.26.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Stolidus Filius ſum calamitas ſuus Pater, 19.13.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Qui maledico ſuus Pater, aut ſuus Mater, lucerna is extinguo in tenebrae, 20.20.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Quiſquis diripio ſuus Pater aut ſuus Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; dico ſum nullus defectio; idem ſum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius interfector, 28.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Fear.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Reverentia Jehova adjicio dies, vero annus improbus decurto, 10.27.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Reverentia Jehova ſum ſcaturigo vita, ad recedo a tendicula mors, 14.27.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Reverentia Jehova ſum eruditio ſapientia, &amp; ante honor ſum abjectio, 15.33.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:27"/>4. Reverentia Jehova ſum odi malum, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, elatio &amp; via mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, &amp; os perverſus odi, 8.13.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In reverentia Jehova ſum fiducia validus, &amp; is filius benedico poſt is, 14.26.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Benignitas &amp; veritas iniquitas ex pio, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentia Jehova homo recedo a malum, 16.6.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Melior ſum parum cum reverentia Jehova, quam amplus theſaurus &amp; vexatio cum ille, 15.16.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Reverentia Jehova tendo ad vita, &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus is commoror ſatur, non viſito malum, 19.23.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Humilitas &amp; reverentia Jehova ſum divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae &amp; honor &amp; vita, 22.4.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Revereor Deus, &amp; obſervo Praeceptum, is ſum totus homo, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.13.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Quamvis Peccator facio malum centies, &amp; dies ille Prorogo, tamen certe ſcio ſum be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne timens Deus qui timeo a facies is, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.12.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Revereor Jehova &amp; Rex, ne commiſceor ille qui ſum deditus mutatio, 24.21.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Beatus ſum ille qui paveo jugiter: autem qui obduro ſuus animus ruo in malum, 28.14.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Tremor homo pono tendicula; autem qui confido Jehova, ſum tutus, 29 25.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:28"/>
                  <head>Feaſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Convivium paror ad laetitia, &amp; Vinum lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifico, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Fire.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Poſſum quiſquam accipere ignis in ſinus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, nec is veſtis aduror, 6.27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Friend.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui benedico ſuus amicus magnus vox, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens tempeſtivè mane, imputor maledictio is, 27.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Fool.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Stolidus non delector intelligentia; niſi ut ſuus animus prodo ſui ipſius, 18.2.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Stultus habeo Jocus Peccatum; ſed inter rectus ſum benevolentia, 14.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Stolidus ſermo ineo contentio, &amp; in os ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voco contuſio, 18.6.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Stultus indignatio cito agnoſco, vero pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens tego ignominia, 12.16.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Etiam ſtultus dum ſileo reputo ſapiens, &amp; qui obturo labium ſuus habeo homo intelligens, 17.28.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Sum ludus ſtolidus facio ſcelus, at homo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligens exerceo ſapientia, 10.23.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Excellens ſermo decet non ſtultus, multo minus mentiens labium Princeps, 17.7.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:29"/>8. Sum honorificus vir ſupercedo a lis; autem omnis ſtultus immiſceo ſe, 20.3.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Omnis prudens ago cum ſcientia; autem ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidus pando ſuus ſtultitia. 13.16.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Quamvis contundo ſtultus in mortarium cum mola piſtillum, tamen is ſtultitia non recedo ab ipſe, 27.22.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Increpatio uro magis prudens quam cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum plaga ſtolidus, 17.10.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Quare ſum pretium in manus ſtolidus ad poſſideo ſapientia, cum deſum ille animns, 17.16.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Sapientia ſum coram prudens; autem o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus ſtolidus vagor ad extremitas terra, 17.24.</p>
                  <p n="14">14 Os ſtultus ſum baculus ſuperbia, vero la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium ſapiens conſervo ipſe, 14.3.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Animus ſapiens adſum dextera, vero a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus ſtolidus is finiſtra, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.2.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Sapientia requieſco in animus intelligens; autem qui ſum in ſtolidus exhibeo cognoſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, 14.33.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. Loquor ne in auditio ſtolidus, nam ſperno prudentia tuus dictum; 23.9.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. Videone vir ſapiens in oculus ſuus? ſum melior expectatio de ſtolidus quam de ille, 26.12.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. Corona ſapiens ſum ille divitiae; at ſtul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titia ſtolidus maneo ſtultitia, 14.24.</p>
                  <p n="20">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:30"/>20. Animus ſapiens ſum in locus luctus, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem animus ſtolidus ſum in locus laetitia, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.4.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. Pes claudus non ſum aequus, ita ſum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia in os ſtolidus, 26.7.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. Ut ſpina venio in manus Ebrius, ita ſum ſententia in os ſtolidus, 26.9.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. Ut canis redeo ad ſuus vomitus, ita ſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ad ſuus ſtultitia, 26.11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. Lapis ſum gravis, &amp; arena ponderoſus; ſed ſtultus indignatio ſum gravior ille duo, 27 3.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. Urſa orbatus ſuus catulus occurro vir poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us quam ſtolidus in ſuus ſtultitia, 17.12.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. Verbum ſapiens audio cum quies potius quam clamor ille qui dominor inter ſtultus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.17.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. Stoliditas pono in celſus dignitas, vero di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves ſedeo in abjectus locus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.6.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. Ut qui applico lapis baliſta, ita facio ille qui praebeo honor ſtolidus, 26.8.</p>
                  <p n="29">29. Flagellum equus, fraenum aſinus, ita virga ſtolidus tergum, 26.3.</p>
                  <p n="30">30. Qui conturbo ſuus domus, poſſideo ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, &amp; ſtultus efficior ſervus ſapiens animus; 11.29.</p>
                  <p n="31">31. Abeo a conſpectus ſtolidus vir, quum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio non in ille verbum ſcientia, 14.17.</p>
                  <p n="32">32. Sum melior audio increpatio ſapiens, quam audio canticum ſtolidus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.5.</p>
                  <p n="33">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:31"/>33. Qui ambulo cum ſapiens fio ſa piens; vero ſocius ſtolidus corrumpo, 13.20.</p>
                  <p n="34">34. Qui mitto verbum per ſtolidus, detrunco pes &amp; ebibo paena, 26.6.</p>
                  <p n="35">35. Mortuus muſca efficio unguentum Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macopola eructo faetor; ita parvus ſtultitia il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le qui aeſtimor propter ſapientia &amp; gloria, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.1.</p>
                  <p n="36">36. Stultitia ſtolidus ſum dolus, 14.8.</p>
                  <p n="37">37. Magnus ille Deus qui formo omnis, &amp; compenſo ſtultus, &amp; compenſo tranſgrediens, 26.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Friend.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Vir qui habeo amicus debeo praebeo ſui a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micus; ſum amicus qui haereo conjunctior frater 18.24.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Ferrum acuo ferrum; ita vir acuo facies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micus, 27.17.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Qui amo mundites animus, pro gratia is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium Rex ſum futurus ille amicus, 22.11.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Tuus amicus &amp; paternus amicus derelinquo ne, 27.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Froward.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Nequam homo, improbus vir ambulo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus os, 6.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui habeo perverſus animus conſequor nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus bonum, 17.20.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:32"/>3. Perverſus vir immitto contentio; &amp; ſuſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus disjungo charus amicus, 16.28.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Aculeus &amp; laqueus ſum in via perverſus; qui obſervo ſuus anima ſum procul ab is, 22.5.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Praefractus ſum abominatio Jehova, autem arcanum is ſum apud rectus, 3.32.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Os juſtus profero ſapientia, vero perverſus lingua reſcindo, 10.31.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Removeo abs tu perverſus os, &amp; pravus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium amoveo procul abs tu, 4.24.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="g" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Gift.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Homo donum do acceſſus is, &amp; adduco ille coram magnates, 18.16.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Donum in abditum averto ira, &amp; munus in ſinus vehemens excandeſcentia, 21.14.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Munus ſum veluti gratiſſimus gemma in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus poſſidens ille; quocunque ſpecto proſperor, 17.18.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Improbus accipio munus é ſuus ſinus ad per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verto iter jus, 17.23.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Qui ſum deditus quaeſtus conturbo ſuus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, vero qui odi donum vivo, 15.27.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Quiſquis jacto de falſus donum, ſum vel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t vapor &amp; ventus ſine pluvia, 25.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:33"/>
                  <head>Goods.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Cum bonum augeor, ille multiplicor, qui comedo: ergo quis commodum ſum Dominus is praeter aſpectus cum ſuus oculus? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Grave.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Quiſquis tuus manus aſſequor ut facio, facio pro tuus facultas: nam ſum nullus opus, nec ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiocinium, nec ſcientia, nec ſapientia in ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrum quo eo, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sum tres qui nunquam ſatio, imo quatuor dico non ſum ſatis, ſepulchrum &amp; oculus, uterus, terra qui non ſatio aqua, &amp; ignis qui dico non ſum ſatis, 30.15.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="h" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Hand.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Si facio ſtulte effero tu; aut ſi cogito malum impono manus os, 30.32.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Rex animus ſum in manus Jehova, ut rivus aqua, inclino is quocunque volo, 21.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Haſty.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Video ne vir praeceps in ſuus verbum? ſum melior expectatio de ſtultus quam de ille, 29.20</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui ſum tardus ad ira ſum magnus intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia, autem qui ſum praeceps animus excito ſtultitia, 14.29.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:34"/>3. Ne prodeo feſtinanter ad litigo, ne ignoro quid facio tandem quum tuus proximus adduco tu ad ignominia, 25.8.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Ne accelero tuus os, &amp; ne tuus animus fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtino profero quiſquam coram <hi>Deus;</hi> nam Deus ſum in coelum, at tu ſuper terra, idcirco tuus verbum ſum paucus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Hatred.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Odium excito contentio, verò charitas ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tego omnis defectio, 10.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui tego odium fallax labium, qui profero infamia, ſum ſtolidus. 10.18.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Melior ſum cibarium olus ubi ſum dilectio, quam ſaginatus bos &amp; odium cum ille. 15.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Head.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Tuus veſtimentum ſum ſemper nitidus; &amp; tuus caput careo ne unguentum, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.8.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Ornamentum juvenis ſum ille vis, &amp; deco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fenex ſum canites, 20.29.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Canites ſum Corona gloria, ſi invenio in via juſtitia, 16.31.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Heart.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Meus filius do ego tuus cor, &amp; tuus ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus obſervo meus via, 23.26.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Homo animus excogito ſuus via, ſed Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va ſtatuto ille greſſus, 16.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:35"/>3. Homo animus agnoſco ſuus amaritudo, &amp; extraneus non intermiſceo ſui in is laetitia, 14.10.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Laetus animus facio laetus vultus, 15.13.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Laetus animus benefacio tanquam medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na; autem fractus ſpiritus excicco os, 17.22.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Sum melior adeo locus luctus, quam locus convivium; nam ille ſum finis omnis homo, &amp; vivens indo ſuus animus, <hi>Ec.</hi> 7.2.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Ut qui eripio veſtis in frigus tempus, &amp; ut acetum nitrum, ita ſum qui cano canticum male affectus animus; 25.20.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Stultitia homo perverto ipſe via, &amp; is ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus indignor adverſus Jehova, 19.3.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Animus prudens quaero ſcientia, autem os ſtolidus paſcor ſtultitia, 15.14.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Lingua juſtus ſum ut lectiſſimus Argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum animus improbus ſum preparvi, 10.20.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Qui confido ſuus animus ſum ſtultus, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem qui ambulo ſapienter is eripio, 28.26.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Coelum altitudo terra Profunditas, &amp; ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Rex ſum inſcrutabilis, 25.3.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Fuſoreus vas argentum, &amp; Catinus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum; at Jehova Probo cor, 17.3.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Infernus &amp; perditio ſum coram Jehova; quanto magis animus filius homo, 15.11.</p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:36"/>15. Ut facies obverſor facies, ita animus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo homo, 27.19.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Quis poſſum dico purifico meus animus, ſum mundus a meus peccatum? 20.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Honey.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Invenio Mel? comedo qui ſum ſatis tu, ne ſaturor is, &amp; evomo, 25.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Honour.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui ſector juſtitia &amp; benignitas, conſequor vita, juſtititia &amp; honor, 21.21.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Gratioſus mulier contineo honor, &amp; poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior contineo divitiae, 11.16.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Homo elatio deprimo is, autem honor ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtento depreſſus ſpiritus, 29.23.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Qui cuſtodio ficus comedo fructus ille, ita qui obſervo ſuus Dominus honoro, 27.18.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In multitudo populus ſum Rex decor, at in defectus natio ſum contritio dominator, 14.28.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Ut nix in aeſtas, &amp; pluvia in meſſis, ita ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor non convenio ſtultus, 26.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Hope.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Spes protractus efficio animus aeger; autem cum deſiderio advenio ſum Arbor vita, 13.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:37"/>2. Enim is qui aſſocio omnis vivens ſum ſpes, quippe vivens Canis ſum melior mortuus Leo, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Spes juſtus ſum laetitia, vero expectatio im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probus pereo, 10.28.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Quum improbus homo morior is expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio pereo, etiam ſpes injuſtus pereo, 11.7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Houſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Domus improbus perdo, autem tentorium rectus floreo, 14.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Jehova evello domus ſuperbus, autem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituo terminus vidua, 15.25.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Improbus everto nec ſum, autem familia juſtus ſto, 12.7.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In domus juſtus ſum multus opes, at in proventus improbus ſum perturbatio, 15.6</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Sapientia domus aedifico, &amp; intelligentia ſtabilio, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.3.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Contineo tuus pes à tuus proximus domus, ne ſaturor tu, ac ita odio habeo tu, 25.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:38"/>
                  <head>Humble.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Melior ſum ſubmiſſus ſpiritus cum manſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etus, quam partior ſpolium cum ſuperbus, 16.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Homo elatio deprimo is, autem honor ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tento depreſſus ſpiritus, 29.23.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Facio iſte jam meus Filius &amp; eripio tu quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do convenio in manus tuus Proximus, age ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jicio tu, &amp; interpello tuus Proximus, 6.3.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Quum homo deprimo tum tu dico ſum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altatio, &amp; ſervo demiſſus homo, <hi>Job</hi> 22.29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Hunger.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Pigritia injicio altus ſopor, &amp; ignavus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima eſurio, 19.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Homo non contemno fur, ſi furor ad expleo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uus animus quum eſurio, 6.30.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Satur anima calco favus, vero famelicus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima omnis amarus ſum dulcis, 27.7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Hypocrite.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Hypocrita os corrumpo ſuus Proximus, at ſcientia juſtus libero, 11.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Triumphus improbus ſum brevis &amp; laetitia hypocrita uſque ad momentum, <hi>Job</hi> 20.5.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Quis ſum expectatio hypocrita quamvis lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cror, quum Deus decutio is defiderium, <hi>Job</hi> 27.8.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:40"/>4. Ne Hypocrita regno ne populus illaqueo, <hi>Job</hi> 34.30.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="i" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Increaſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Honoro Jehova de tuus ſubſtantia, &amp; de primitiae totus tuus proventus, 3.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Sum qui diſpergo tamen augeo, &amp; ſum qui cohibeo plus aequus at tendo ad egeſtas, 11.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Inheritance.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sapientia ſum bonus cum poſſeſſio, &amp; per is ſum emolumentum aſpiciens Sol, <hi>Ec.</hi> 7.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Bonus trado poſſeſſio filius filius, &amp; opes peccator recondo juſtus, 13.22.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Poſſeſſio poſſum acquiro feſtinanter in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium, autem finis ille non benedico, 20.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Inſtruction.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Adhibeo tuus Animus ad eruditio, &amp; tuus auris ad ſermo ſcientia, 23.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Audio eruditio, &amp; ſapio &amp; ne averto ille, 8.33.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Qui amo eruditio, amo ſcientia, vero qui odi correptio ſum brutus, 12.1.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Sum in iter vita qui ſervo eruditio, vero qui derelinquo correptio erro, 10.17.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:41"/>5. Praeceptum ſum lucerna, &amp; doctrina ſum lux, &amp; correctio eruditio ſum via vita, 6.23.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Do eruditio ſapiens, &amp; amplius ſapio, docco juſtus, &amp; creſco ſub doctrina, 9.9.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Qui nolo eruditio ſperno ſuus anima, autem qui auſculto correptio poſſideo animus, 15, 32.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Paupertas &amp; ignominia ſum avertens ab e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruditio, autem qui ſervo correptio honoro, 13.18.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Prehendo eruditio, ne demitto, cuſtodio ille quia ſum tuus vita, 4.13.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Deſino meus filius auſculto eruditio, qui facio aberro a ſermo ſcientia, 19.27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Integrity.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Integritas rectus deduco is, at perverſitas perfidioſus devaſto is, 11.3.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Melior ſum pauper qui ambulo in ſuus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritas ille qui ſum perverſus ſuus labium, &amp; ſum ſtolidus, 19.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Iudgment.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Rex iudicium ſtabilio regio, vero qui ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio munus deſtruo is, 29.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Multus quaero dominans favor, verum u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſquiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> jus ſum a Jehova, 29.29.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:42"/>3. Multus cibus ſum in cultura pauper, ſed ſum qui conſumo prae inopia judicium 13.23.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Qui obſervo praeceptum experior non ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus res, &amp; ſapiens animus novi &amp; tempus &amp; ratio, <hi>Ec.</hi> 8.5.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Quoniam quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> voluntas ſub tempus &amp; ratio; ideo m iſeria homo ſum magnusille, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8 6.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Vaſtitas improbus diſſeco ipſe; quia re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuo exerceo jus, 21.7.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Judicium paro in deriſor, &amp; contuſio in tergum ſtolidus, 19.29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Iuſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sum laetitia juſtus facio jus, vero contritio ſum operor iniquitas, 21.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Juſtus ambulo in ſuus integritas ille filius ſum beatus poſt is, 20.7.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Iter juſtus ſum ſimilis ſplendidus lux qui luceo magis magiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad perfectus dies, 4.18.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Memoria juſtus ſum, benedictus autem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men improbus putreſco, 10.7.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Improbus irretio a defectio ſuus labium, at juſtus egredior ab anguſtia, 12.13.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Juſtus cado ſepties &amp; exurgo rurſus, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro improbus corruo in malum, 24.16.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:43"/>7. Qui abſolvo improbus, &amp; qui condemno ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus aeque ambo ſum abominatio Jehovah, 7.15.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Multo juſtus non ſum bonus, nec percutio Princeps propter aequitas, 17.26.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="k" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>King.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Divinus Sententia inſideo labium Rex, is os non praevaricor in judicium, 16.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sum abominatio Rex committo improbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, nam ſolium ſtabilio juſtitia, 16.12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Juſtus labium ſum dilitiae Rex, &amp; diligo loquens rectum, 16.13.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Rex infideo ſolium judicium ventilo omnis malum ſuus oculus, 20.8.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Sapiens rex ventilo improbus, &amp; converto rota in ille, 20.26.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Sum honor Deus abſcondo res; antem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor Rex perveſtigo res, 25.2.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Ubicunque Verbum Rex ſum, ibi ſum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatio; ecquis dico Rex, Quis facio? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Job</hi> 34.18.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Excandeſcentia Rex ſum ut nuntius mors, ſed ſapiens vir expio is, 16.14.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Rex indignatio ſum ut rugitus Leo, autem is benevolentia ſum ut ros ſuper Herba, 19.12.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:44"/>10. In lux Rex facies ſum vita, iſque bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volentia ſum velut nubes ſerotinus pluvia, 16.15.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Rex qui fideliter judico tenuis, ipſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium ſtabilio in perpetuum, 29.14.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Abſum Rex bibo vinum, nec Domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor inebrians potus; ne bibo &amp; obliviſcor ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; muto jus ullus afflictus, 31.4, 5.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Hei tu Regio, cum tuus Rex ſum puer, &amp; tuus Princeps comedo mane, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.16.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Aufero improbus a conſpectus Rex, &amp; is ſolium ſtabilio juſtitia, 25.5.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Ne maledico Rex, ne quidem in tuus animus, &amp; ne maledico dives in tuus conclave; nam avis caelum perfero vox, &amp; ales indico verbum, <hi>Ec.</hi> 10.20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Knowledge.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sum aurum &amp; copia carbunculus; at labi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſcientia ſum pretioſus gemma, 20.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Accipio meus eruditio, ac non pecunia: &amp; ſcientia potius quam lectiſſimus aurum, 8.10.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Ut animus careo ſcientia non ſum bonus; &amp; qui propero pes pecco, 19.2.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:45"/>4. Vir qui poſſideo ſcientia cohibeo ſuus ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo; &amp; vir intelligens ſum eximius ſpiritus, 17.27.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Sapientia ſum umbra, &amp; pecunia ſum um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra; ſed excellentia ſcientia ſum, quod ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia confero vita poſſeſſor, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.12.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="l" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Labour.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. In omnis labor ſum emolumentum; at verbum labium tendo ad egeſtas, 14.23.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui laboro, laboro ſuimet, nam is os rogo hic ille, 16.26.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Omnis labor homo obvenio ipſe os, tamen deſiderium non ex pleo, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 6.7.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Subſtantia acquiſitus ex vanitas diminuo; autem qui congrego manus augeo, 13.11.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Singulus res ſum plenus labor, homo non poſſum eloquor, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.8.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Enim ſum homo qui labor conficior ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia, &amp; ſcientia, &amp; aequitas; autem homo qui non laboro in ille trado in ille pars, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.21.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Sum nil melior homo quam ut comedo, &amp; bibo, &amp; ut efficio ſuus animus fruor bonum ex ſuus labor, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.24.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:46"/>8. Unuſquiſque etiam qui Deus do divitiae &amp; facultas, &amp; facio is copia comedo ex ille, &amp; percipio ſuus pars, ac laetor de ſuus labor; hic ſum donum Deus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.19.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Qui ſum homo ex omnis ſuus labor; &amp; ex afflictio ſuus animus qui ille laboro ſub Sol? <hi>&amp;c. Eccl.</hi> 2.22.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Quemadmodum prodeo ex ſuus Mater uterus, nudus reverto ut venio, &amp; reporto ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ex ſuus labour qui defero in ſuus manus, <hi>Ec.</hi> 5.15.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Hic etiam ſum magnus malum; quod omnino prout venio ita abeo, &amp; quis emolumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſum is qui laboro in ventus? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 6.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Land.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui colo ſuus tellus habeo copia panis; vero qui ſector vanus homo ſum demens &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior paupertas, 28.19. <hi>cum</hi> 12.11.</p>
                  <p>Ne moveo antiquus terminus qui tuus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jores apto, 22.28.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Propter defectio Regio multus ſum Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps is: autem ad homo prudens &amp; peritus ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus illi prorogo, 28.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:47"/>
                  <head>Laughter.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Etiam inter riſus animus doleo, &amp; finis ille laetitia fio maeror, 14.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Ego dico de riſus, ſum inſanus; &amp; de lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titia ecquis facio iſte? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Luctus ſum melior riſus, quia triſtitia vultus animus efficio melior, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.3.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Tempus fleo, &amp; tempus rideo, tempus plango, &amp; tempus ſalto, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.4.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Ut crepitus ſpina ſub olla ita ſum riſus ſtolidus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.6.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Convivium paro ad laetitia &amp; vinum lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifico; at pecunia ſuficio res omnes, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Law.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Doctrina ſapiens ſum ſcaturigo vita, ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedo a tendicula mors, 13.14.</p>
                  <p>Quûm non ſum viſio, populus pereo; autem qui obſervo Lex, beatus ſum ille; 29.18.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Qui derelinquo Lex, laudo improbus; at qui obſervo Lex, contendo cum ille, 28.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Liberal.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Beneficus animus efficio pinguis, &amp; qui rego etiam ipſe. 11.25.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:48"/>
                  <head>Lips.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Labium juſtus paſco multus; vero ſtul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus morior prae dementia, 10.21.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Labium juſtus experior quis ſum gratus; verò os improbus loquor perverſus, 10.32.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Labium ſapiens ſpargo ſcientia; autem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus ſtolidus facio non ita, 15.7.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Labium prudens ſapientia adſum; at vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga ſum tergum demens, 10.13.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Verbum ſapiens os ſum gratioſus; vero labium ſtolidus abſorbeo ſui, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.12.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Ardens labium, &amp; impius cor, ſum ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis teſta obductus argenteus ſcoria, 26.23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Lot,</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sors conjicio in gremium; totus ratio is ſum a Jehova, 16.33.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sors facio contentio ceſſo, &amp; dirimo inter robuſtus; 18.18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Lye.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Maleficus attendo ad falſus labium; &amp; mendax adverto ad erumnoſus lingua, 17.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Mendax lingua odi ille qui attero ab ille; &amp; blandus os perficio ruina, 26, 28.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:49"/>3. Elatus oculus &amp; mendax lingua, Deus odi, 6.17.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Qui loquor mendacium non evado, 19.5, 6.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Mendax lingua duro tantum ad momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, 12.19.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Mendax labium ſum abominatio Jehova, autem q i ago fideliter ſum is delectatio, 12.22.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Juſtus odi mendacium; vero improbus ſum faetidus, atque pudefio, 13.5.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Acquiſitio theſaurus per mendax lingua, ſum vanitas impulſus huc &amp; illuc quaerens mors, 21.6.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Amoveo longe â me vanitas &amp; mendaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, 30.8.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="m" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Mercy.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Benignitas &amp; fides cuſtodio Rex, &amp; ille ſolium ſuſtento benignitas, 20.28.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Benignus vir benefacio ſuus anima; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem crudelis turbo ſuis caro, 11.17.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Qui contemno ſuus proximus pecco au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem qui facio gratia pauper, beatus ſum ille, 14.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Meſſenger.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Improbus nuncius incido in malum; at fidelis legatus ſum ſalus, 13.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:50"/>2. Ut frigus nivalis tempus meſſis, ita ſum fidus legatus mittens ipſe; nam reſtituo ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſuus dominus, 25.13.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Malus quaero tantum rebellio; idcirco crudelis nuntius mitto in is, 17.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Money.</head>
                  <p n="1">1, Pecunia reſpondeo omnis res, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Morrow.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Glorior ne de dies craſtinus, quia neſcio quid dies pario, 27.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Mouth.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Quiſque comedo bonum ex fructus ſuus Os; vero anima perfidioſus comedo violentia, 13.2.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Vir ſatio bonum ex fructus ſuus Os; &amp; retributio ſuus manus reddo ille, 12.14.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Quiſque venter ſatio fructus Os; &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventus ſuus labium ipſe ſatio, 18.20.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Qui cuſtodio ſuus Os, conſervus ſuus vita; ſed qui divarico ſuus labium invenio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritio, 13.3.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Benedictio rectus Urbs effero; autem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruo Os improbus, 11.11.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:51"/>6. Verbum improbus inſidior ſanguis; autem Os rectus eripio ille, 12.6.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Illaqueo a ſermo tuus Os: capio ſermo tuus Os, 6.2.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Stolidus Os ſum is contritio, &amp; is labium ſum tendicula illa vita, 18.7.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Permitto ne tuus Os ut facio tuus caro pecco, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.6.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="n" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Name.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Bonus nomen ſum optatior amplus divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae; &amp; gratia melior argentum &amp; aurum, 22.1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Bonus fama ſum melior pretioſus unguen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum; &amp; dies mors dies nativitas, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.1.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Nomen Jehovah ſum robuſtus turris; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus accurro ille &amp; ſum ſalus, 18.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Naught.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sum peſſimus ſum peſſimus, aio emptor; ſed quum digredior tum glorior, 20.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Neighbour.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Melior ſum vicinus qui ſum propinquus, frater qui ſum longinquus, 27.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui careo ſapientia ſperno ſuus proximus, at vir prudens ſileo, 11.12.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:52"/>3. Dico ne tuus proximus ab eo deinde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertor, &amp; cras do; quum ſum penes tu, 3.28.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Vir qui blandior ſuus amicus, pando rete pro is, 29.5.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Ut inſaniens qui jaculor fax, ſagitta &amp; lethale; ita ſum ille qui decipio ſuus proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; dico, Nonne ludo? 26.18.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Net.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Fruſtra rete pandor ante oculus quivis ales, 1.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>News.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Ut frigidus aqua feſſus anima, ita ſum bonus auditio è longinquus terra, 25.25.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="o" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Oppreſsion.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui opprimo tenuis probro afficio is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pifex; autem qui honoro hic facio gratia e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens, 14.31.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Pauper vir qui opprimo tenuis ſum ſimilis everrens pluvia qui relinquo nullus panis, 28.3.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Oppreſſio facio ſapiens inſanus, &amp; dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio perdo animus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.7.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Princeps qui careo intelligentia ſum du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus oppreſſor; autem qui odi quaeſtus prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go dies, 28.26.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:53"/>5. Conſidero omnis oppreſſio qui fio ſub Sol, autem ecce lachrymae is qui opprimo, &amp; ſum ille nullus conſolator; &amp; penes opprimens ſum vires. Idcirco laudo mortuus qui ſum jam mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus prae vivus qui adhuc vivo, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.1.2.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Si video oppreſſio pauper, &amp; violentus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terverſio jus &amp; juſtitia in provincia, miror ne de iſte inſtitutum; nam qui ſum altior altiſſimus obſervo, &amp; ſum ſuperior iſte, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Ox.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Ubi non Bos ſum, praecipe ſum mundus; autem multus proventus ſum vis Bos, 14.4.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="p" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Paſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Is qui ſum, ſum jam; &amp; qui ſum futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus jam ſum, autem Deus repeto praeteritus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Pit.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui fodio fovea decido in is; &amp; qui de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volvo lapis revertor in ipſe, 26.27.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui facio rectus vago in malus via decedo ipſe in ſuus fove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; vero integer poſſideo bonus, 28.10.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:54"/>3. Qui fodio foſſa, cado in is; &amp; qui perrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po maceria, Serpens mordeo is, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Poor.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui amo laetitia ſum egens vir; qui amo vinum &amp; unguentum non ſum dives, 21.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sum qui cohibeo plus aequus, &amp; tendo ad egeſtas, 11.24.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Qui ſector vanus homo, ſatior paupertas, 28, 19</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Verſor ne inter ebrius, inter vorator caro; nam ebrioſus &amp; comeſſator vergo ad pauperies; &amp; dormitatio induo homo panunculus, 23.20, 21.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Diligo ne ſomnus, ne advenio ad paupertas; aperio tuus oculus, &amp; ſatio panis, 20.13.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Adhuc pauculus ſomnus pauculus dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio, pauculus complicatio manus ad dormito; Ita tuus paupertas advenio ut viator, &amp; tuus egeſtas tanquam clypeatus vir, 24.33, 34.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Qui accelero ad diteſco, habeo malignus oculus, &amp; ignoro inopia obvenio ſui, 28.22.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Redemptura vir vita ſum ſuus divitiae; at pauper audio non increpatio, 13.8.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:55"/>9. Sum qui jacto ſui dives, tamen habeo ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil; ſum qui fingo ſui pauper, tamen habeo amplus ſubſtantia 13.7.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Deſiderium homo ſum ipſe benignitas; &amp; pauper ſum melior mendax, 19.22.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Melior ſum pauper ambulans in ſuus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritas ille, qui ſum perverſus in ſuus iter quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis ſum dives, 28.6.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Subſtantia addo multus amicus; autem tenuis disjungo a ſuus proximus, 19.4.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Omnis frater pauper odi ille, quanto magis is ſocius abſum procul ab ille. Perſequor ille verbum tamen ille non remaneo, 19.7.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Pauper deteſtor etiam a ſuus proximus, 14.20.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Dives Dominor in pauper, &amp; mutuans ſum ſervus dans mutuum 22.7.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Pauper cloquor ſupplicatio; autem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves loquor aſpere, 18.23.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. Sum generatio qui dens ſum ut gladius, &amp; is molaris dens ut culter; ad conſumo pauper è terra &amp; egens ab homo, 30 14.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. Diripio ne tenuis eo quod ſum tenuis; neque contero pauper in porta, 22.22.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. Qui opprimo tenuis ut amplifico ſuus res &amp; qui do dives, certe devenio ad egeſtas, 22, 16.</p>
                  <p n="20">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:56"/>20. Qui ſubſanno pauper, convitior is opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fex; &amp; qui delector calamitas, non ſum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punis, 17.5.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. Dives &amp; pauper occurro una; Jehova ſum Creator uterque, 22.2.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. Qui largior pauper mutuo Jehova; &amp; qui do ille rependo, 19.17.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. Juſtus cognoſco cauſa tenuis; at impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus animadverto non ut cognoſco, 29, 7.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. Qui habeo benignus oculus benedico; nam do de fuus panis tenuis, 22.9.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. Qui obturo ſuus auris a clamor tenuis; etiam clamo ipſe at non exaudio, 21.13.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. Aperio tuus os, judico juſte, &amp; ago cauſa pauper &amp; egens, 31.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Portion.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Do pars ſeptem, aut etiam octo; nam ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcio quis malum ſum futurus ſuper terra, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Praiſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sicut conflatorius vas argentum, &amp; cati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus aurum, ita ſum vir ſecundum ſuus laus, 27.21.</p>
                  <p n="2">2, Extraneus laudo tu, autem non tuus os; alienus, autem non tuus labium, 27.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:57"/>
                  <head>Pride.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Solus ſuperbia prodeo jurgium, at penes conſultus ſum ſapientia, 13.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Quum ſuperbia advenio, tum ignominia evenio; autem apud modeſtus ſum ſapientia, 11.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Elatus oculus, &amp; ſuperbus cor, &amp; aratio im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probus ſum peccatum, 21.4.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Omnis altus animus ſum abominatio Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va; licet vis conjungor, non ſum impunitus, 16.5.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Qui ſum ſuperbus animus miſceo conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio; autem qui confido Jehova efficior pinguis, 28.25.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Melior ſum finis res principium is; &amp; longanimis quam elatus animus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.8.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Superbus &amp; contumax, deriſor ſum ipſe nomen, qui ago cum ſuperbus excandeſcentia, 21.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Prudent.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Callidus homo tego ſcientia, autem ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ſtolidus proclamo ſtultitia, 12.23.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sapientia aſtutus ſum conſidero ſuus via, 14.8.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Sapiens animus voco prudens; autem ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitas labium addo ſcientia, 16.21.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Aſtutus praevideo malum, &amp; abſcondo ſui; autem fatuus tranſeo &amp; mulcto, 22.3.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:58"/>5. Fatuus credo omne verbum, autem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtutus adverto ad ſuus greſſus, 14.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Prince.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Oblectatio non decet ſtultus; multo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſervus dominor in Princeps, 19.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Multus precor favor Princeps, &amp; quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſum amicus vir dans munus, 19.6.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Longanimitas ductor pellicio, 25.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Proclaim.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Plurimus homo praedico quiſque ſuus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitas; autem verax vir, quis invenio? 20.6.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="q" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Quiet.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Quicunque auſculto ſapientia habito ſecure, &amp; ſum tranquillus a pavor malum, 1.33.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Melior ſum ſiccus bucca &amp; tranquilitas cum is, quam domus plenus ſacrificium cum contentio, 17.1.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Melior ſum plenus volo cum quies, quam ambo pugnus plenus cum moleſtia &amp; afflictio ſpiritus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.6.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="r" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Rebuke.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Manifeſtus correptio ſum melior occultus amor, 27.5.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Deriſor auſculto non increpatio, 13.1.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:59"/>3. Ille qui corripio improbus ſum amoenitas; &amp; bonus benedictio obvenio is, 24.25.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Qui erudio deriſor, recipio ſui ignominia; &amp; qui corripio improbus recipio ſui convitium, 9.7.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Qui corripio homo, poſtea conſequor ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor gratia, quam qui blandior lingua, 28.23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Recompence.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Ne dico rependo malum; autem expecto Jehova &amp; ſervo tu, 20.22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Reprover.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Velut monile aureus, &amp; ornamentum ex inſignis aurum; ita ſum ſapiens reprehenſor auſcultans auris 25.2.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Virga &amp; correptio do ſapientia, 29.15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Correctio eruditio ſum via vita. 6.23.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Qui obſervo correptio, poſſideo intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia, 15.32.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Auris auſcultans correptio vita commoror inter ſapiens, 15.31.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Corripio ille qui poſſideo prudentia: &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligo ſcientia, 19.25.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Corripio ne deriſor ne odi tu; corripio ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piens, &amp; amo tu, 9.8.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Qui derelinquo correptio erro, 10.17.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:60"/>9. Qui odi correptio, ſum brutus, &amp; mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, 12.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.10.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Vir qui ſaepius correptus, obduro ſuus cervix; repente confringo idque ſine curatio, 29.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Reſpect.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Non ſum bonus agnoſco perſona in judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, 24.23.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Agnoſco perſona non ſum bonus; nam propter bucca panis ille vir deficio, 28.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Rich.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Laboro ne ut diteſco; deſiſto a tuus pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia, 23.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Divitiae non proſum dies furor; autem juſtitia eripio a mors, 11.4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Figo occulus in ille qui ſum non; enim opes certe comparo ſui ala, ut Aquila verſus Coelum, 23.5.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Divitiae ſum non in ſeculum, &amp; an coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na maneo in quique generatio? 27.24.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Somnus laborans ſum dulcis, ſive comedo parum ſive multum: autem ſaturitas dives non permitto is ut dormio. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.12.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Fidelis vir abundo benedictio; at qui prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipito ad diteſco non ſum innocens, 28.20.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:61"/>7. Qui confido ſuus divitiae decido; at juſtus effloreſco tanquam ramus, 11.28.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Dives ſubſtantia ſum is munitus Urbs, &amp; tanquam editus murus in ipſe cogitatio. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritio tenuis ſum is paupertas, 18.11. &amp; 10.15.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Dives habeo multus amicus, 14.20.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Do ego nec paupertas nec divitiae, alo ego cibus conveniens ego, 30.8.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Sum magnus malum qui video ſub Sol, ſcilicet, divitiae aſſervatus dominus ſuus in ipſe malum. At ille divitiae pereo malus occupatio; &amp; gigno Filius &amp; ſum nihil in is manus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.13, 14.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Vir qui Deus do divitiae, facultas &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, adeo ut deſtituor nullus res pro ſuus anima ex omnis qui concupiſco; tamen Deus facio is non copia comedo ex ille, ſed alienus comedo ille: hic ſum vanitas, &amp; malus aegritudo, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 6.2.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Scientia penetrale impleo omnis pretio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus &amp; amaenus opes, 24.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Righteous.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Juſtus ſum excellentior ſuus proximus; at via improbus ſeduco is, 12.16.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Os juſtus ſum ſcaturigo vita; at violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia obtego os improbus, 10.11.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:62"/>3. Labium Juſtus paſco multus, vero ſtultus morior prae dementia, 10.21.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Piger deſidero totus dies, vero Juſtus do neque parco, 21.16.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Quum Juſtus impero populus laetor; autem quum improbus dominor, populus ſuſpiro, 29.2.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Defectio malus vir inſum tendicula; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem juſtus canto &amp; laetor, 29.6.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Quum Juſtus exulto, ſum amplus ornatus; autem quum improbus erigor homo occulto, 28.12.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Quum benefit juſtus Urbs exulto, &amp; quum improbus pereo exerceor cantus, 11.10.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Juſtus curo vita ſuus jumentum; autem miſeratio improbus ſum crudelis, 12.10.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Qui loquor veritas, indico Juſtitia; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem falſus teſtis dolus, 12.17.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Juſtus prudenter conſidero domus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probus; at Deus everto improbus propter ille impietas, 21.12.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Improbus fugio nemo perſequens; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem juſtus ſum audax tanquam Leo, 28.1.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Via piger ſum ſepimentum ſpina; autem iter rectus planus, 15.19.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:63"/>14. Fructus juſtus ſum arbor vita; &amp; qui capio anima ſum ſapiens. 11.30.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Labor juſtus tendo in vita; proventus improbus ſum peccatum, 10.16.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Improbus deſidero rete malus: ſed radix Juſtus do fructus, 12.12.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. Timor improbus evenior is; autem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderium juſtus do, 10.24.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. Jehova abſum procul ab improbus; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem exaudio oratio juſtus, 15.29.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. Juſtus libero ex anguſtia, &amp; improbus devenio in is locus, 11.8.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. Improbus ſum redemptio pro juſtus; &amp; perfidus pro rectus, 21.18.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. En juſtus remunero in terra; multo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis improbus &amp; peccator, 11.31.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. Quum improbus creſco defectio creſco; vero juſtus video is caſus, 29.16.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. Malum inſector peccator; autem juſtus bonum compenſo, 13.21.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. Juſtus comedo ad ſatietas ſuus anima; autem venter improbus egeo, 13.25.</p>
                  <p n="25">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:64"/>25. Jehova non ſino juſtus eſurio; autem depello ſubſtantia improbus, 10.3.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. Ut turbo tranſeo, ſic exiſto improbus non amplius; vero juſtus ſum perpetuus funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, 10.25.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. Juſtus nunquam dimoveo; vero impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus non habito terra, 10.30.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. Homo non ſtabilio improbitas; autem radix juſtus non dimoveo, 12.3.</p>
                  <p n="22">22 Lux juſtus laetor, at lucerna improbus extinguo, 13.9.</p>
                  <p n="30">30. Via improbus ſum abominatio Jehova; autem diligo is qui ſector juſtitia, 15.9.</p>
                  <p n="31">31. Melior ſum parum cum juſtitia, quam ampliſſimus proventus ſine jus, 16.8.</p>
                  <p n="32">32. Juſtitia exalto gens; autem peccatum ſum probrum omnis populus, 14.34.</p>
                  <p n="33">33. Theſaurus improbitas proſum non; ſed juſtitia eripio a mors, 10.2.</p>
                  <p n="34">34. Improbus facio fallax opus; vero ſerens juſtitia ſum fidus merces, 11.18.</p>
                  <p n="35">35. Juſtitia integer dirigo is via; at impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus concido ſuus improbitas, 11.5.</p>
                  <p n="36">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:65"/>36. In iter juſtitia ſum vita, &amp; in ſemita is ſum non mors, 12.28.</p>
                  <p n="37">37. Juſtitia cuſtodio integer in via; vero improbitas perverto peccator, 13.6.</p>
                  <p n="38">38. Ut juſtitia tendo ad vita, ſic qui ſector malum ſector ad ſuus mors, 11.19.</p>
                  <p n="39">39. Ne inſidior (O improbus) habitaculum juſtus; devaſto ne is accubitus, 24.15.</p>
                  <p n="40">40. Juſtus cadens coram improbus ſum, ut conturbatus fons, &amp; corruptus ſcaturigo, 25.26.</p>
                  <p n="41">41. Qui dico improbus, tu ſum juſtus; is populus execror, natio deteſtor, 24.24.</p>
                  <p n="42">42. Ne ſum juſtus nimium, nec ſimilo tu ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium ſapiens; quare perdo tu ipſe? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.16.</p>
                  <p n="43">43. Omnis evenio aeque omnis; ſum idem eventus juſtus &amp; improbus, bonus, &amp; mundus, &amp; immundus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Rule.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui dominor in ſuus animus, ſum melior is qui capio civitas, 16.32.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui habeo nullus imperium in ſuus ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus, ſum ſimilis Civitas diſruptus &amp; abſque murus, 25.28.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:66"/>3. Sum tempus quid homo dominor in homo in ille malum, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.9.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Ut rugens Leo, &amp; diſcurſans Urſus; ita ſum improbus Dominator in tenuis populus, 28.15.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Si Dominator attendo mendacium, omnis is miniſter ſum improbus, 29.12.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Si ſpiritus Dominator effero ſe contra tu, deſero ne tuus locus; nam ſubmiſſo ſedo mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus peccatum, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.4.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Ne ſum avidus cupediae rector; enim ſunt mendax cibus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.3.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="s" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Sacrifice.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sacrificium improbus ſum abominatio Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hova; autem oratio rectus ſum is oblectatio, 15.8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sacrificium improbus ſum abominatio, quanto magis quum offero ille ſceleratus ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus? 21.27.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Exerceo juſtitia &amp; jus, ſum magis dilect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Jehova quam Sacrificium, 21.3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Safety.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Equus apto ad praelium; ſed ſalus ſum â Jehova, 21.31.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Scorn.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Deriſor quaero ſapientia nec invenio; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſcientia ſum facilis prudens, 14.6.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:67"/>2. Deriſor non diligo ille qui corripio ipſe, nec adeo ſapiens, 15.10.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Ejicio deriſor, ſimul contentio exeo; imo litigium &amp; ignominia ceſſo, 22.19.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Deriſor duco Urbs in inſidiae; at ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens averto ira, 29.8.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Percutio deriſor, &amp; fatuus caveo, 29.15.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Quum deriſor mulcto fatuus reſipiſco; &amp; quum ſapiens inſtruo percipio ſcientia, 21.11.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Deus derideo deriſor, autem do gratia manſuetus, 3.34.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Deriſor ſum abominatio homo, 24.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Seaſon.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Quiſque res ſum occaſio; &amp; quiſque vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas ſum tempus &amp; ratio, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Seed.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Mane ſero tuus ſemen, &amp; veſpere ne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitto tuus manus; nam ignoro, <hi>&amp;c. Eccl.</hi> 11.6</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Silver.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui amo pecunia, non ſatior pecunia; &amp; qui amo abundantia, cum proventus; <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:68"/>
                  <head>Servant.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Ne accuſo ſervus apud ſuus dominus, ne maledico tu, &amp; peragor reus, 30.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Intelligens ſervus dominor in filius pude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faciens, &amp; partior poſſeſſio inter frater, 17.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Rex benevolentia ſum erga intelligens ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus; autem is furor ſum contra pudefaciens, 14.35.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Qui delicate educo ſervus a pueritia, red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do is filius tandem, 29.21.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Quum ſervus regno terra commoveo, 30.21.22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Slothful.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Piger dico ſum Leo in via, occido in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tea; 26.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Piger condo ſuus manus in ſuus gremium, &amp; dolet ille reduco is ad ſuus os, 26.15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Piger ſum ſapientior in ſuus oculus, quam ſeptem vir qui poſſum reddo ratio, 26.16.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Ut janua circumagor in cardo, ita piger in ſuus lectus, 26.14.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Deſiderium piger occido is, quia is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus renuo laboro, 21.25.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Via piger ſum ſepimentum ſpina, 15.19.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:69"/>7. Qui eſt remiſſus in ſuus opus, ſum frater diſperdens, 15.19.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Tranſeo juxta ager piger, &amp; juxta vinea homo demens; autem ecce totus tego carduus, &amp; urtica tego ſuperficies is, &amp; lapideus mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria is deſtruo, 24.30, 31.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Multus pigritia contignatio attenuor, &amp; demiſſio manus domus perſtillo, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.18.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Pigritia injicio in altus ſopor, &amp; ignavus anima eſurio, 19.15.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Piger non aro propter hyems; idcirco mendico in aeſtus, &amp; habeo nil, 20.4.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Ut acetum dens, &amp; velut fumus oculus; ita ſum piger mittens ipſe, 10.26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Spirit.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Anima homo ſum lucerna Jehova, perve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigans omnis penetrale venter, 23.27.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Quis animadverto ſpiritus humanus qui aſcendo ſurſum, &amp; ſpiritus beſtia qui deſcendo deorſum ad terra? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.21.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Quemadmodum ignoro qui ſum via ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, nec quomodo os formor in uterus gravida; ita ignoro opus Deus qui creo omnis, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.5.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:70"/>4. Sum nullus homo qui dominor ſpiritus ut contineo ſpiritus; neque habeo dominatio in dies mors, &amp; ſum nullus miſſile in iſte praelium; nec impietas libero is qui ſum deditus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.8.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Spiritus vir ſuſtento ſuus aegritudo, autem fractus ſpiritus quis ſuſtento? 18.14.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Dolor animus ſpiritus frangor, 15.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Stones.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui amoveo lapis, dolore afficior is; &amp; qui findo lignum, periclitor is, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Study.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Facio Liber ſum nullus finis; &amp; multus lectio ſum fatigatio caro, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Sun.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Nil novus ſub Sol, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Strife.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Initium contentio ſum quaſi cum quis laxo aqua; quare deſero lis antequam agito, 17.14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Preſſura lac educo butyrum, &amp; preſſura naſus educo ſanguis; ita preſſura ira educo lis, 30.33.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:71"/>3. Diligo defectio qui diligo jurgium; &amp; qui amplio ſuus janua quaero fractura, 17.19.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Ubi nullus lignum ſum ignis extinguor; ita ubi non ſum ſuſurro contentio ſileo, 26.20.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Iracundus vir miſceo contentio; autem qui ſum tardus ad ira ſedo lis, 15.18.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Qui tranſeo &amp; excandeſco in lis qui per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet non ad ipſe, ſum ſimilis ille qui prehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do canis auris, 26.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Surety.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Ne ſum ex ille qui ferio manus, aut ex ille qui ſum ſponſor pro debitum: ſi non ſum tu qui reddo, quare accipio tuus cubile a tu? 22.26, 27.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Homo demens complodo manus &amp; fio ſponſor, ante ſuus amicus, 17.18.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Capio is veſtis qui ſpondeo pro extrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp; accipio pignus ab is pro alienus mulier, 20.16.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Meus filius ſi ſpondeo pro tuus amicus, ſi complodo tuus manus cum extraneus, illaqueo ſermo tuus os, capio ſermo tuus os, 6.1, 2.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Qui ſpondeo pro extraneus confringor; autem qui odi ſponſio ſum ſecurus, 11.15.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="t" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:171177:72"/>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Tale-bearer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Suſurro revelo arcanum, at qui ſum fidus animus tego res, 11.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Verbum ſuſurro ſum ut vulnus, &amp; deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do in penetrale venter, 18.8.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Qui ambulo ſuſurro revelo arcanum; er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go commiſceor ne cum ille qui adulor ſuus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium, 20.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Thief.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Quicunque partior cum Fur, odi ſuus ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; audio execratio at indico non, 29.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Thoughts.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Cogitatio ſtultitia ſum peccatum, 24.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Cogitatio malus ſum abominatio Jehova; autem ſermo mundus ſum amaenus ſermo; 15.26.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Devolvo tuum factum in Jehova, &amp; tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us cogitatio ſtabilio, 16.3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Tongue.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Mors &amp; vita ſum in poteſtas lingua, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que amo is comedo fructus is, 18.21.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui obſervo ſuus os &amp; lingua, conſervo ſuus anima ab anguſtia, 21.23.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:73"/>3. Salutifer lingua ſum arbor vita; autem per verlitas in is ſum confractio ſpiritus, 15.4.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Mollis lingua frango os, 25.15.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Virtute preditus faemina aperio ſuus os fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienter, &amp; is lingua inſideo doctrina benignitas, 31.26.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Sum qui pronuncio ſimilis transfoſſio gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius; at lingua ſapiens ſum medicina, 12.18.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Boreas diſpello pluvia; ita indignabundus vultus ſimulans lingua, 25.23.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Qui ſum verſutus lingua incido in malum, 17.20.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Lingua juſtus ſum velut lectiſſimus argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, 10.20.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Lingua ſapiens utor ſcientia bene: autem os ſtolidus eructo ſtultitia, 15.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Tree.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sive decido Arbor ad Meridies, ſive ad Aquilo, ubi Arbor cado ibi ſum futurus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Truth.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Meus palatum effero veritas; &amp; impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitas ſum abominatio meus labium, 8.7.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Labium veritas ſtabilio in aeternum, 12.19.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:74"/>3. Comparo veritas ac vendo non, etiam ſapientia, &amp; eruditio &amp; prudentia, 23, 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Truſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Confido in Jehova ex totus tuus animus vero innitor ne tuus intelligentia 3.5.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="v" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Vanity.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui ſemino iniquitas, meto vanitas, &amp; virga ſuus furor deficio; 22.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Violence.</head>
                  <p>Malus veſcor cibus improbitas, &amp; bibo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num violentia, 4.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Homo qui exerceo violentia in ſanguis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, fugeo ad fovea, ne quis ſuſtento is, 28.17.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Anima perfidioſus comedo violentia, 13.2.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Violentus vir pellicio ſuus proximus, &amp; duco is in via iniquus, 16.29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Beatus ſum homo qui conſequor ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, &amp; homo qui obtineo intelligentia, 3, 13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sapientia ſum praecipuus res, ideo acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro ſapientia; &amp; cum totus tuus acquiſitio acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro prudentia, 4.7.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Quantum melior comparo ſapientia, quam aurum? &amp; comparo prudentia ſum optatior ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentum? 16.16.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:75"/>4. Intelligentia ſum ſcaturigo vita poſſidens ipſe, at eruditio ſtultus ſum ſtultitia, 16.22.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Rectus intelligentia do gratia; autem via perfidia ſum aſper, 13.15.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Solertia obſervo tu, intelligentia cuſtodio tu, 2.11.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Qui poſſideo ſapientia, diligo ſuus anima, qui obſervo intelligentia conſequor bonum, 19.8.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Homo qui aberro a via intelligentia, quieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co in caetus mortuus, 21.16.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Dico Sapientia tu ſum meus foror, &amp; voco prudentia tuus affinis, 7.4.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Sum nullus ſapientia, intelligentia, aut conſilium adverſus Jehova, 21.30.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Vngodly</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Nequam vir effodio malum, &amp; is labium infideo adurens ignis, 16.27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Vnjuſt.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Qui faenus &amp; injuſtus lucrum augeo ſuus ſubſtantia, &amp; congrego is pro ille qui largior tenuis, 22.8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Iniquus vir ſum abominatio juſtus, &amp; qui ſum rectus in ſuus via, ſum abominatio impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, 29.27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:76"/>
                  <head>Vpright.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Deus facio homo rectus; autem ipſo quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro plurimus ratiocinium, <hi>Eccl,</hi> 7.29.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui ſum perverſus animus, ſum abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Jehova; at qui ſum integer in ſuus via ſum ille oblectatio, 11.20.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Iter juſtus ſum recedo a malum, at qui cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodio ſuus via conſervo ſuus anima, 16.17.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Qui ambulo in ſuus integritas revereor Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hova; vero qui ſum praefractus in ſuus via ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no is, 14.2.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Qui ambulo integre, ambulo ſecure; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem qui pervertus ſuus via innoteſco, 10.9.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Via Jehova ſum robur integer, autem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritio ſum operans iniquitas, 10.29.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Deus repono verus ſapientia pro rectus, ſum ſcutum ambulans integre, 1.7.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Improbus vir obfirmo ſuus facies; autem rectus ipſe apto ſuus via, 21.29.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Qui ambulo integro ſervo; vero qui ſum perverſus in ſuus via cado ſubito, 28.18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:77"/>
                  <head>Vow.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sum tendicula homo, deglutio ſacer, &amp; poſt votum inquiro, 20.25.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="w" type="part">
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Water.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Aqua furtivus ſum ſuavis, &amp; cibus come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus in latebrae ſum amoenus. 9.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Way.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sum via qui videor rectus homo, ſed fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis is ſum via mors, 14.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Via improbus ſum caligo, neſcio in quis impingo, 4.19.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Iter vita ſum ſurſum intelligens, ut recedo a ſepulchrum deorſum, 15.24.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Auſculto jam meus filius &amp; ſapio, ac di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigo tuus animus in via, 23.19.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Ambulo per via bonus, &amp; obſervo iter ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, 2.20.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Vir greſſus ſum a Jehova, quomodopoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum homo ergo intelligo ſuus via? 20.24.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. In omnis tuus via agnoſco is, &amp; ipſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigo tuus iter, 3.6.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Expendo orbita tuus pes, &amp; omnis tuus via ſtabilio, 4.26</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Deus cuſtodio iter jus, &amp; conſervo via ſanctus, 2.8.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:78"/>10. Sum tres qui ſum nimis occultus ego, imo quatuor qui novi non; via Aquila in Coelum; via Serpens in rupes; via Navis in medium Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; &amp; via Vir cum Virgo. 30.18, 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wander.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Ut Avicula qui erro a nidus ſuus, ita ſum vir qui erro a locus ſuus, 27.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wealth.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Subſtantia acquiſitus ex vanitas diminuo; autem qui congrego manus augeo, 13.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Homo quicunqus Deus do divitiae &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultas, &amp; facio copia comedo ex ille, &amp; percipio ſuus pars, ac laetor de ſuus labor; hic ſum donum Deus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Water.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Bibo aqua e tuus ciſterna, &amp; fluentum e tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us puteus, 5.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Tuus fons ſpargo paſſim, &amp; rivus aqua in platea; ſum tantum tuus, ac non extraneus cum tu, 5.16, 17.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Verbum humanus os ſum velut profundus aqua, &amp; ſcaturigo ſapientia ſimilis eructans torrens, 18.4.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:79"/>4. Projicio tuus panis in aqua, nam invenio is poſt multus dies, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Weight.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Diverſus pondus, &amp; diverſus menſura, uterque ſum aeque abominatio Jehova, 20.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Diverſus pondus ſum abominatio Jehova, &amp; doloſus bilanx non ſum bonus, 20.23.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Juſtus trutina &amp; bilanx ſum Jehova, &amp; omnis pondus loculus ſum is opus, 16.11.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Doloſus bilanx ſum abominatio Jehova; vero integer pondus ſum is delectatio; 11.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wicked.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Sum ne nimium improbus, neque ſum ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidus; quare morior ante tempus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Ingredior ne iter improbus, neque ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do per via malus, 4.14.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Improbus adveniens advenio etiam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptus, cum ignominia probrum, 18.3.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Nullus moleſtia evenio juſtus, autem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probus impleo malum, 12.21.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Animus improbus deſidero malum, ipſe proximus invenio non gratia in is oculus, 21.10.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Suus iniquitas capio improbus ipſe, &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo funis ſuus peccatum, 5.22.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Succenſeo ne propter maleficus, neque in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>video improbus, 24.19.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:80"/>8. Vidi improbus ſepultus, qui accedo, &amp; abeo e locus ſanctus, &amp; ſum oblivioni traditus in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitas cum ita facio: hic etiam ſum vanitas, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.10.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Jehova operor omnis propter ſui, etiam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probus ad dies malum, 16.4.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Sum nullus merces malus; lucerna im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probus extinguo, 24.20.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Bonus adipiſcor benevolentia a Jehova; at vir ſceleratus machinatio condemno, 12.2.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Ne timeo a repentinus pavor, nec a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatio improbus quum advenio, 3.25.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Improbus excindo e terra, &amp; perfidus avello ex is, 2.22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wife.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Domus &amp; divitiae ſum poſſeſſio pater, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem intelligens uxor ſum a Jehova, 19.14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui conſequor uxor conſequor bonus, &amp; acquiro benevolentia a Jehova, 18.22.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Tuus ſcaturigo ſum benedictus, laetor de uxor tuus adoleſcentia, 5.18.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Vivo jucunde cum uxor qui amo, omnis dies vita tuus vanitas, qui do tu ſub Sol; nam ille ſum tuus pars in hic vita, &amp; in tuus labor qui ſubeo ſub Sol, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.9.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:81"/>5. Stolidus filius ſum calamitas pater, &amp; jui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium uxor ſum continuus ſtilla, 19.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wind.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Quis emolumentum ſum is qui laboro pro ventus? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.16.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Qui obſervo ventus, non ſemino; &amp; qui reſpicio nubes, non meto, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wine.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Vinum ſum deriſor inebrians, potus ſum tumultuoſus; quiſquis oberro in is non ſapio, 20.1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Quis ſum calamitas? quis dolor? quis ſum contentio? quis ſum loquacitas? quis ſum vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus? quis ſum rubor oculus? Quis immoror diu apud vinum? qui eo ad inveſtigo miſtus vinum, 23.29.30.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Reſpicio ne in vinum quum rubeſco, quum exhibeo ſuus color in poculum, quum moveo ſui recte. Tandem mordeo velut Serpens, &amp; pungo ut Haemorrhous. Tuus oculus reſpicio alienus mulier, &amp; tuus animus eloquor perverſus, 23.31, 32.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Do inebrians potus periturus, &amp; vinum ille qui ſum amarus animus bibo, &amp; obliviſcor ſuus paupertas, &amp; recordor ſuus moleſtia non amplius, 31.6, 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171177:82"/>
                  <head>Wiſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Inclino tuus auris, &amp; auſculto verbum ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, &amp; adhibeo tuus animus ad ſcientia, 22.17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Meus filius, ſi tuus animus ſapio, meus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus laetor, inquam meus, 23.15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Sapiens audio &amp; adjicio diſciplina, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligens comparo induſtrius conſilium, 1.5.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Multitudo verbum abſum non peccatum; ſed qui cohibeo ſuus labium, ſum ſapiens, 10.19.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Animus ſapiens moderor ſuus os, &amp; addo diſciplina ſuus labium, 16.23.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Sum theſaurus deſideratiſſimus, &amp; oleum in habitaculum ſapiens; autem ſtolidus homo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorbeo ille, 21.20.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Hic etiam pertinet ad ſapiens; non ſum bonus agnoſco perſona in judicium, 24.23,</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Verbum ſapiens ſum inſtar aculeus, &amp; cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus infixus ab autor collectio, qui ſum datus ab unus paſtor, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.11.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Sum quatuor qui ſum parvus in terra, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſum valde ſapiens, Formica, Cuniculus, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſta &amp; Aranea, 30.24.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Abeo ad formica O piger, aſpicio is via, &amp; ſapio, 6.6.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:83"/>11. Si ſapiens contendo cum ſtolidus, ſive commoveor, ſive rideo tamen nullus ſum quies, 29.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wiſdom.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Ego ſapientia habito cum prudentia, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venio ſcientia ſummus ſolertia, 8.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sapientia ſum melior carbunculus, &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis qui poſſum deſidero non ſum aequandus is, 8.11.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Sapientia ſum melior arma bellum, vero unus peccatum perdo multus bonum, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.18.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Sapientia ſum melior robur; nihilominus ſapientia indigus deſpicio, &amp; is verbum non audio, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.16.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Sapienta corroboro ſapiens magis, quam decem dominator qui ſum in civitas, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.19.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Sapientia ſum nimis altus ſtultus, non ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio ſuus os in porta, 24.7.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Qui tracto res ſapienter conſequor bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp; qui confido beatus ſum ille, 16.20.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Ad deſiderium ſeparatus, quaero &amp; inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſceo ſe in omnis ſapientia, 18, 18.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Ne dico, quis ſum cauſa, quare prior di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſum melior iſte? nan non rogo ſapienter de hic, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.10.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:84"/>10. Multus ſapientia inſum multus indignatio &amp; qui augeo ſcientia, augeo dolor, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.18</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Witneſs.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Jehova odi falſus teſtis conflans menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium, 6.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Fidus teſtis non mentior; autem falſus teſtis eflo mendacium, 14.5.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Falſus teſtis non ſum impunis; qui loquor mendacium non evado, 19.5.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Mendax teſtis pereo, autem vir qui au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſculto loquor in aeternum, 21.28.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Vir qui teſtor falſus teſtimonium contra ſuus proximus, ſum marculus, &amp; gladius, &amp; acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſagitta, 25.18.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Verax teſtis libero anima; autem doloſus conflo mendacium, 14.25.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Nequam teſtis derideo jus, &amp; os abſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo iniquitas, 19.28.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Ne ſum teſtis contra tuus proximus teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; nec decipio tuus labium, 24.28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Woman.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Stolidus mulier ſum ſtrepitus, &amp; fatuus, &amp; novi nihil, 9.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Labium extraneus mulier ſtillo tanquam favus, is pallatum ſum mollior oleum; attamen is finis ſum amarus ut abſinthium, acutus ut bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pennis gladius; ille pes deſcendo ad mors, is greſſus apprehendo ſepulchrum, 5.3, 4.5.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:85"/>3. Sapientia Eripeo tu ab extraneus mulier, ab alienigena qui blandio ſuus dictum; qui dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquo dux ſuus adoleſcentia, &amp; obliviſcor foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſuus Deus: nam is domus propendeo ad mors, &amp; is orbita ad mortuus, 2.16, 17, 18.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Facio tuus iter procul ab extraneus mulier, &amp; ne appropinquo oſtium ille domus; ne cedo tuus decor alius, &amp; tuus annus crudelis; ne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traneus ſatior tuus facultas, &amp; tuus labor ſum in domus alienus, tuque gemo tandem cum tuus caro &amp; corpus conſumo, ac dico quomodo odi eruditio, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 5.9.10, 11, 12.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Sub tres terra commoveo, imo ſub qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor qui non poſſum fero; ſub ſervus quum reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, ſtultus quum ſaturo cibus; ſub exoſus mulier quum marito, &amp; ſub ancilla, qui ſum haeres ſuus hera, 30.20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Invenio amarior mors, faemina qui ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ſum rete &amp; plagae, &amp; ille manus ut vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum; quiſquis placeo Deus, liberor ab is; vero peccator capior ab is, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.26.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Os extranea ſum profundus foſſa; qui ſum abominandus Jehova corruo in ille, 22.14.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Ne dedo tuus robur faemina nec tuus via ille qui deleo rex, 31.3.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:86"/>9. Quare tu meus filius oblector extraneus mulier, &amp; amplector pectus aliena; nam via homo ſum coram oculus Jehova, &amp; expendo omnis is orbita, 5.20, 21.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Obſervo praeceptum, &amp; ſervo tu a male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficus mulier, a blanditia lingua aliena: deſidero ne is pulchritudo in tuus animus, neque capio tu ſuus palpebra, 6.24.25.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Ut monile aureus in porcus roſtrum; ita ſum pulcher mulier ſine prudentia, 11.22.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Strenuus uxor ſum corona ſuus maritus; ſed qui pudefacio ſum tanquam putredo ille os, 12.4.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Quiſque ſapiens faemina aedifico ſuus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; autem ſtultus faemina deſtruo is ſuus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, 14.1.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Sum melior habito in angulus tectum, quam cum contentioſus mulier in communis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, 25.24.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Sum melior habito in deſertum, quam cum contentioſus &amp; indignabundus mulier, 21.19.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Quis invenio ſtrenuus faemina; nam is pretium ſupero carbunculus, 31.10.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. Unus homo inter mille invenio, at faemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na inter omnis iſte non invenio, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.28.</p>
                  <p n="18">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171177:87"/>18. Gratia ſum fallax &amp; pulchritudo ſum vanus; at mulier qui revereor Jehova, ipſe lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. Do is de fructus is manus, &amp; proprius fact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um laudo is in porta, 31.30, 31.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. Quicunque abſcondo litigioſus mulier, abſcondo ventus; &amp; unguentum dexter ipſe qui prodo ſeſe, 27.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Word.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Anxietas in animus vir deprimo ille; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem bonus verbum laetifico ille, 12.25.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Amaenus ſermo ſum ut mel favus, dulcis anima, &amp; ſalus os, 16.24.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Verbum commode dictus, ſum ſimilis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum aureus in tabula argenteus, 25.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proverbs">
                  <head>Wrath.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Homo iracundus ſubeo paena; enim ſi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitto is, tamen mulcto amplius, 19.19.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
